<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The seat of the scorner thrown down, or, Richard Hobbs his folly, envy and lyes in his late reply to my book called A looking-glass, &amp;c manifested and rebuked whereunto is annexed my call from the Baptists, to walk in the true light : and a true testimony to the light and power of Christ in the heart with a few queries to the said R. Hobbs / by Luke Howard ; to which is added a further answer by T.R.</title>
            <author>Howard, Luke, 1621-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44639</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2987</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6501</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13505987</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13505987</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99793</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44639)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99793)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 791:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The seat of the scorner thrown down, or, Richard Hobbs his folly, envy and lyes in his late reply to my book called A looking-glass, &amp;c manifested and rebuked whereunto is annexed my call from the Baptists, to walk in the true light : and a true testimony to the light and power of Christ in the heart with a few queries to the said R. Hobbs / by Luke Howard ; to which is added a further answer by T.R.</title>
                  <author>Howard, Luke, 1621-1699.</author>
                  <author>Howard, Luke, 1621-1699. Looking-glass for Baptists.</author>
                  <author>Rudyard, Thomas, d. 1692. Water-Baptists reproach repeld.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>59 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The Water-Baptists reproach repeld" signed at end: Thomas Rudyard.</note>
                  <note>"A looking-glass for Baptists" and "The Water-Baptists reproach repeld" each has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduced from original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hobbs, Richard, 17th cent. --  Quakers looking glass look'd upon.</term>
               <term>Howard, Luke, 1621-1699. --  Looking-glass for Baptists.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99793:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99793:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SEAT OF THE SCORNER Thrown Down: OR, <hi>Richard Hobbs</hi> his Folly, Envy and Lyes in his late Reply to my Book, called, <hi>A Looking-Glaſs, &amp;c.</hi> Manifeſted and Rebuked.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed my Call from the <hi>BAP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TISTS,</hi> to walk in the True LIGHT.</p>
            <p>And a True Teſtimony to the Light and Power of Chriſt in the Heart.</p>
            <p>With a few QUERIES to the ſaid <hi>R. Hobbs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Luke Howard.</p>
            <p>To which is added, a further Anſwer by <hi>T. R.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>He that is firſt in his own Cauſe, ſeemeth Juſt; but his Neighbour co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth after, and ſearcheth him out,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 18.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>The Lip of Truth ſhall be eſtabliſhed forever; but a Lying Tongue is but for a Moment,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 12.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:99793:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99793:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>INto whoſe hands this may come, for your ſakes who are ſo much troubled, that there ſhould be ſo much contending, and as you ſay, <hi>ſtriving</hi> betwixt People profeſſing Religion; this know, that we called <hi>Quakers</hi> are forced thereunto, and that for Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſake; for the Lord knows it is ſo, becauſe the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> began firſt with us: as ſoon as the King gave Liberty, they fell on us, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>laying to our Charge things we knew not,</hi> of Lying Stories of ſeven Years old out of <hi>Lincolnſhire</hi> of one <hi>Richard Anderſon</hi> of <hi>Panton,</hi> which never was at a <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> Meeting in his Life, but at many <hi>Baptiſts</hi> Meetings as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by their own Writing, and ſo in Hypocriſie would cloath him with a <hi>Quaker</hi> by Name, who was rather a <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> and only becauſe he at ſome times (after his own manner) would ſpeak of the Light Within (againſt them) which Light theſe Men ſo hate, that for a little ſpoken from a Man which was never one of us, neither in Reality, nor yet in Formality, they ſhould make ſo much a do, and ſuch a Cry of to the World, as they have done, and would have the World judge of the Light of Chriſt, which we ſay every Man is lighted with, by the Carriage of him who was ſo near themſelves.</p>
            <p>And now mark, becauſe our Friends gave an Anſwer in plain Truth to their falſe Charge, <hi>Richard Hobbs</hi> Paſtor of the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> in <hi>Dover,</hi> as he calls himſelf, in Envy undertook to write a Relation of one <hi>Charles Bayly,</hi> of his <hi>Miſcarriages</hi> Ten or
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99793:3"/>Eleaven Years old; and becauſe a deal of his Mad Actions were true (for which he muſt bear his own Burden) therefore they thought that that ſhould crown their Lyes in their former Story from <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colnſhire,</hi> and ſo they Printed them together: but his ſpirit, to wit, <hi>C. B.</hi> and his Work, we did and do deny, as by the <hi>Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Glaſs for Baptiſts</hi> doth at large appear, unto which I refer the Reader. So that I am thus conſtrained for Righteouſneſs ſake to appear in Print once more, by way of Reply unto this Scoffer's <hi>Night-Labour,</hi> a Work which he hath been Sixteen Years exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing in; and of late he hath began in Print to ſhew the Fruit of his Labour againſt the Light Within, and ſnarling at the Heels of thoſe who believe in it: and although he reads in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which he calls <hi>his Rule, That many are Called, and few Choſen;</hi> yet is his Eye ſo watching for Evil, that the Fall of one Called and not Choſen is to him a rich Feaſt, as appears by his firſt and ſecond Printing of the Miſcarriages of one <hi>Charles Bayly;</hi> and if his laſt had not been redoubling of his Evil in Envy in his firſt by Lying, Scoffing and Mocking, I might have reſted at this time in Silence; knowing right well, that my firſt Anſwer to his Envious Charge againſt the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, is clear enough (without <hi>Rubbing,</hi> as he ſcoffingly calls it) to his firſt, and might have ſerved for this ſecond alſo to all Impartial Minds.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Luke Howard.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="apology">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99793:3"/>
                  <head>THE Seat of the Scorner Thrown Down, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>ANd now Reader, becauſe I am accuſed in pag. 9. of this <hi>Night-Watch-man</hi>'s Labour, <hi>of my leaving the Ordinances of God,</hi> as he calls them. I ſhall here give a brief Account of my leaving the People called <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in their <hi>carnal Water-dipping</hi> and <hi>elementary Worſhip,</hi> where I with many more were, as now many are looking for the Living among the Dead; and in our meeting in thoſe dayes, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming our Work and Duty as we then thought, in that which we call'd <hi>Goſpel-Faith,</hi> even then would God's Witneſs the <hi>Light</hi> ariſe, and ſhew me, <hi>that we were not in the Goſpel-Faith,</hi> which we ſo much profeſſed; <hi>and that we were not Baptized by the One Spirit into the One Body:</hi> Here the Lord in the Light put me to a ſtand, and ſet me ſpiritually to commune with my own Heart in a weighty Senſe of my own Condition, and then in the Light I ſaw, <hi>That we were all ignorant of the One Baptiſm and One Faith, as well as of the One Lord and one Body, into which that Baptiſm gives an enterance.</hi> It is true, we were dipped in Water in Hope of Life and Peace, and call'd <hi>Brothers</hi> and <hi>Siſters</hi> by <hi>Water-dipping;</hi> but that <hi>Formality ſatisfied not the Cry of my Soul,</hi> which was ſtill in me after ſpiritual Knowledge and Acquaintance with the Lord, which by the Light ſhining in my Heart I ſaw was not to be had in <hi>carnal Water,</hi> notwithſtanding Men do ſo much quote <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. for <hi>Water-dipping,</hi> unto which in the <hi>Baptiſts Looking-Glaſs</hi> I have ſpoken fully in pag. 12, 13. unto which I refer the Reader. But to return, Then I became very much diſſatisfied, and conſtrain'd to for ſake thoſe things &amp; People in their Obſervations, and that for <hi>good Conſcience ſake,</hi> which I once practiced, while the Vail was over my Heart, in a Day of great
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99793:4"/>Reproach; &amp; here I was willing to forget thoſe that things were behind in the Death, and preſs forward after Life, which they in their dayes were Shaddows of, and that is all they ever were; but now there is but <hi>one Lord, one Faith</hi> and <hi>one Baptiſm.</hi> At that time one of the Preachers asked me (when ſeparated) <hi>Why I would not walk with them?</hi> My Anſwer was, <hi>Becauſe neither they nor I was in the Goſpel. Faith; and that if ever I ſhould know it, that it would be as plain to me as I ſaw the Door with my Natural Eye.</hi> And now hath the Lord ſealed that Faith unto me in the Light, by which I then ſaw my ſelf out of it, everlaſting Praiſes be unto his Name forever: Then my Life became as it were alone, and like a Wanderer ſeeking Reſt; for the Cry continued, and the Witneſs attended, but I knew it not to be the Gift of God's Grace, and <hi>that the Reproof of Inſtruction given by it was the Way to Life,</hi> and ſo took little Warning by it more then to live a kind of a <hi>deſolate Life for want of Peace of Conſcience with the Lord;</hi> and in this State would I Weep and Cry in ſecret for want of true Bread to give Life to my Soul, which lay in Death; yet would I not return again to thoſe empty Shaddows, though im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuned thereunto; but the <hi>Father's Houſe</hi> I ſought, where there was Bread enough, without which I ſhould have periſht forever; yet for all this the Spirit of the World prevailed, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying me captive to the <hi>Law of Sin and Death,</hi> but never into <hi>Lewd Ranting,</hi> as falſly accuſed by this <hi>Night-Watch-man;</hi> in which Day of Diſtreſs and great Loſs came in the Year 1655<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> two of the Servants of the Lord, preaching the Everlaſting Goſpel, which was as Lightning ariſing out of the Eaſt, and ſhining unto the Weſt, even through all in me, to the very Thought in the Heart, by the Word, which is the Searcher and Diſcerner of them, to the reaching unto the <hi>Seed of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and declaring <hi>of a Body of Death ſtanding, notwithſtanding Men's Profeſſion of Religion,</hi> unto which the Witneſs anſwered; ſo that now I knew, <hi>He that believeth the Goſpel hath the Witneſs in himſelf, and out of his Belly ſhall flow Rivers of Living Waters;</hi> this ſpake he of the Spirit, as it is written in the Scriptures of Truth, which are to be read, believed and fulfilled.</p>
                  <p>Reader, this is pretious to read in the Eternal Light and Life,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99793:4"/>and though this was in my Mouth ſweet, yet afterwards it became very bitter in the Daily Croſs to my own Will, and a Day of Sorrow and weeping I knew over him whom I had pierced; ſo when it was Day I wiſhed for Night, and when it was Night I wiſhed for Day; this indeed was a Day of great Diſtreſs, in which I ſaw the <hi>Abomination which made deſolate,</hi> ſtand where it ought not; Then was I to underſtand what it meant, &amp; what God's Will was in it, in making of it manifeſt by his Grace the Light, whoſe Will in the Light and Grace I ſaw was my Sanctification throughout in Soul, Body and Spirit; and here we leave the World that lies in Wickedneſs, and the Profeſſors of the Saints Words, with all that have a Form of Godlineſs without the Power, behind us, in and amongſt the many Opinions and Voices of <hi>Lo here, and Lo there is Chriſt,</hi> and ſo we come to know the Voice of the true Shepherd: whoſe Voice we heard inwardly, and abiding with him, do forever hear in the Light <hi>the Word of Faith in the Heart,</hi> that we may do it: So that now, I ſay, <hi>By the Grace of God and Light within, I am what I am,</hi> and therefore is my Teſtimony amongſt many Brethren, to the <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Light within,</hi> through a living Experience of the good Effects of it, and againſt all theſe <hi>Baptiſt Watchmen of the Night, who plead for Sin term of Life,</hi> and are Backbiters, Slanderers, and Perſecutors of the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; and there will he have his Miniſters conclude their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and his Servants their Work, <hi>who muſt all be paid off with his own Reward of Torment with him and his Angels forever,</hi> which will be alſo the State and Condition of all Hypocrites and Rebellers againſt the Light, if they repent not: And this my Teſtimony agrees with the Teſtimony of the Servants of the Lord in Ages paſt. But to return to that which was to me bitter, when the Lord had lighted my Candle, and with it ſearched my innermoſt Parts, then the Body of Death (out of which ariſeth all Unrighteouſneſs) appeared indeed like a <hi>Mountain of Blackneſs and Darkneſs.</hi> So that I ſaw no Way how to get over it, and was ready to faint in my Mind; but the Lord, whoſe Love is great, and alſo hath Reſpect to the bruiſed Reed and ſmoaking Flax, and will it neither break nor quench,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99793:5"/>until he bring forth Judgment unto Victory, ſupported me by the <hi>more ſure Word of Prophecy, unto the which I did well to take heed as to a Light which ſhined in my dark Heart, untill the Day dawned, and the day Star did ariſe therein;</hi> and then ſprung a ſecret Hope in God, and the Word of his Grace, whoſe promiſe riſe in my Heart, <hi>That he would cleave the Rocks and the Mountains, that the Redeemed of the Lord might come to</hi> Sion: and now Glory be unto his Name, his Promiſe is fulfilled in a good Meaſure, and all along unto this Day, and ſtill is it a ſupport unto me in the midſt of all my Troubles and Tryals in my Travels from Death to Life, in which my Temptations have been many, yea, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many, both within and without, in the Daily Croſs; but ſtill was and is the Lord in the Light a God at Hand, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king good his Promiſes unto his own Seed, in whom they are all yea and amen, ſaith my Soul in a living Experience, in which I have a Teſtimony to bear for the Lord, to the <hi>Grace, Spirit, Light,</hi> and <hi>Life of Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> and that it is <hi>ſufficient for me and all Men in this Age, as it was for</hi> Paul <hi>in that Age and Time of his deepeſt Exerciſes;</hi> for every true Believer hath the Witneſs in himſelf, by a living Experience; and he who hath not, hath no juſt Claim to the Promiſe of God in Chriſt Jeſus, declared of in the holy Scriptures; for the Scriptures were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven forth in the Light, by the Motion of Life in the holy Men of God, as in them it moved, for after Ages to read and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and in the Light to wait for the fulfilling of them; and not for Men to make a Trade and a Gain of, nor yet for Men to live in the Profeſſion of, &amp; take up a Reſt ſhort of the fulfilling of them, as all the <hi>Night-Watch-men</hi> and <hi>Children of the Night</hi> do, who plead againſt the Light, and for Sin term of Life; and ſo can be no true Witneſſes for God in their Generation, though their Profeſſion may be large of the Prophets, Chriſt and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles words, with varieties of Voices and Opinions, crying, <hi>Lo here,</hi> and <hi>Lo there is Chriſt;</hi> but he ſaid, <hi>Believe them not:</hi> for as the Lightning ariſeth in the Eaſt, and ſhineth unto the Weſt (through all) even ſo ſhall be, and ſo is the Coming of the Son of Man, the Second <hi>Adam,</hi> the Quickening Spirit, the Lord from Heaven, who according to the Fleſh is declared to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99793:5"/>be <hi>the Son of David;</hi> but according to the Spirit <hi>the Son of God,</hi> by the Reſurrection from the Dead, which we called <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> believe, and live in the Hope of, witneſs againſt all the <hi>Night-Watch-men</hi> and <hi>Falſe Accuſers,</hi> which ſay we deny it; and herein according to the Spirit, muſt all come to know him, yea, and him worſhip, ſerve, fear and obey, that ever receive Peace by him. And this is a true and Faithful Teſtimony againſt the <hi>Watch-men of the Night,</hi> and the Oppoſers of the Light of Jeſus Chriſt within, born through a living Experience to the Light of Jeſus, which we make mention of, and no other, in whom is Life, and his Life is the Light of Men, to lead all into Salvation that follow it, and to condemn all the Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent unto it; <hi>for this is the Condemnation, that Light is come, and Men love Darkneſs rather then Light, becauſe their Deeds are Evil: and he that loves the Light, brings his Deeds unto it, that he may know they are wrought in God; but he that hates the Light, brings not his Deads unto it, leſt it ſhould reprove them.</hi> And this is my Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, with my many Brethren, and the Saints of old, born to the <hi>Eternal</hi> and <hi>True Light of Chriſt within the Hope of Glory,</hi> and to my <hi>Call out of Darkneſs into Light, and from the Power of Satan to the Power of God;</hi> in which I ſtand a Witneſs for God, and againſt all the Worſhippers of the Beaſt, who have received his Mark in their Fore-heads or Right hands, and therefore plead for his kingdom of Darkneſs, and againſt the Light Within. <hi>Theſe muſt needs be blind Watch-men of the Night, ſaith</hi> Luke How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, <hi>who forſook the People called</hi> Anabaptiſts <hi>and their Water-dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping upon this Account.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply_to_Hobbs">
                  <p>ANd now by way of Reply in Righteouſneſs to this Night Watchman's Scoffing, Mocking and Lying Work; who begins in his Title Page, ſaying, It is a <hi>Sober Reply.</hi> But a ſober Man, ſo made by the Grace of God which teaches So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, will not ſo call a Pamphlet made up of Scoffing and Lying; for in his <hi>Preface</hi> he begins to ſcoff in theſe word, Charles Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>ſometimes a Priſoner upon the Quaking account in</hi> Dover: As
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99793:6"/>if <hi>Quaking</hi> were now become a Scorn and By-word, if it be ſo, it is but to the Fools in Heart, who are ignorant of the Life of <hi>Moſes, Iſaiah, Job, Ezekiel, Daniel, Habakkuk, Jeremiah, Joel</hi> and <hi>Amos,</hi> who were Prophets of the Lord, and all owned <hi>Quaking</hi> and <hi>Trembling</hi> in their Day: And in the ſame <hi>Preface</hi> ſaith he, <hi>But to ſhow, what Enormities the pretended Light leads them to,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>My Anſwer is, <hi>We are Real in our Teſtimony to Chriſt Jeſus the true Light, which lighteth every Man that cometh into the World:</hi> and this, to wit, the <hi>Light, Life</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> which moved in the Holy Men of God to give forth the Scriptures, which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures bear witneſs unto, which is the old time came not by the Will of Man, but Holy Man of God ſpoke as they were Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Holy Spirit; but the Scripture is not that Spirit, nor Life, but teſtifies thereof, nor yet this Night Watch-man's imagination of them, who gives his corrupt Meaning to <hi>Peter's</hi> word<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo Perverts them, ſaying, <hi>He meant the Scriptures, when he ſpoke of the more ſure word of Prophecy, unto the which we do well to take heed as unto a light ſhining in a dark place, until the Day Dawns and the Day Star ariſe in our Hearts,</hi> theſe laſt words (to wit) the Day-Star ariſe in our Hearts, he leaves out, for againſt that (to wit) <hi>Light in the Heart,</hi> are all his Arrows ſhot, this he calls <hi>Erroneous, a dark Light of the Quakers,</hi> or any thing what his dark Mind is pleas'd to call it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he may think, he hath cauſe enough to wreſt the words, and to clip ſome off: for if he teſtifieth againſt the <hi>Quakers</hi> Light, as he ſcoffingly calls it, then he muſt teſtifie againſt <hi>Peter, Paul,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> and the reſt of the Prophets and Apoſtles, for their Teſtimony and ours are one, as may be ſeen more at Large in the Teſtimony following, unto which I Refer the Reader.</p>
                  <p>Then in his firſt Page he begins with three or four Lyes: firſt, he ſaith, that I ſaid, <hi>Some new converted Friends aid own</hi> C. B. when there are no ſuch words in all my Book. Then again he ſaith, <hi>But the Men-Friends in the Caſtle did not own him ſo much:</hi> Theſe are his own words (not mine) to make his foul Work ſeem fair, to make them ſerve his own End, and this he calls, <hi>My appearing with two faces.</hi> So here is a Brat of his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99793:6"/>own begetting in his own Image ſpit out of his own Mouth, ſpeaking his own heart of Lyes in Hypocriſie; for I never ſo ſaid nor meant, for my words were theſe, <hi>Beſide there were ſome at Liberty, which did not own</hi> C. B. <hi>ſo much as</hi> Rich. Hobbs <hi>Repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of,</hi> as may be ſeen in the <hi>Looking-Glaſs</hi> herein Annexed; this his Charging of me with words which I never writ, alters the Matter, and makes it another thing, as any may read that is not Blind.</p>
                  <p>Then again he ſaith, <hi>I Confeſſed I owned</hi> C. B. <hi>as much as the Reſt.</hi> There is no ſuch word in all my Book (as may be ſeen) and although theſe things may ſeem ſmall as here related; yet as they ſtand in his Corrupt Relation in Print, they are Great, becauſe they ſo alter the matter, and makes his Relation have a Face of Fairneſs like Truth: but read my words as they ſtand in my own Book, and his words would be found a Lye, and that a Lye is in his Right-hand, and a deceived Heart hath turned him aſide. And for theſe and ſuch like cauſes to clear the Truth is my former added to this.</p>
                  <p>Again, in pag. 2. he hath this Lye over again, that <hi>I, and three or four in Priſon with me did not own</hi> C. B. <hi>ſo much as Friends at Liberty:</hi> And their he makes Lyes his Refuge, and under Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood he hides himſelf; and when he hath frameth up a Lye, he ſets it up as a Bulwark to batter againſt, with Replies, as if his Lies were mine: and this Courſe this <hi>Night-watch-Man</hi> takes to make a foul thing ſeem fair; and a Lye, which is of the Devil, ſeem true. Several more Lyes I could gather out of his Lying Pamphlet in ſeveral places, where he ſaith I ſaid, <hi>Many of his Flock were of his Mind;</hi> my words were theſe, <hi>As many of his Flock, as were of his Mind:</hi> which alters the matter, and makes it quite another thing; for to my knowledge, <hi>Several of his Flock were not of his Mind.</hi> Then again he ſaith, <hi>that I know my wife reported,</hi> C. B. <hi>had cured her Eyes;</hi> when I know no ſuch thing, but the contrary; and this I can prove by ſeveral Witneſſes.</p>
                  <p>But in this work of bundling up of Lyes I have no delight; but as conſtrained thereunto, to place a few of them upon the Lyers Head, as a Teſtimony againſt the Father of them, who i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:99793:7"/>the Devil; for my Time is precious, and in the Mouth of two or three Witneſſes is every word eſtabliſhed.</p>
                  <p>And then he goes on in like manner of ſcoffing Language in his page 13. That <hi>I beguile the Reader into Fools Paradiſe,</hi> in my ſaying in the <hi>Baptiſts Looking Glaſs, That the</hi> Quakers <hi>worſhip God in Spirit and in Truth, which the Devil, and all that do his Works of Envy</hi> are <hi>out of:</hi> And now if to worſhip God in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and in Truth be <hi>Fools Paradiſe, then what is the wiſe Man's Paradiſe,</hi> ſeeing the Lord ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him, as we do this Day witneſs.</p>
                  <p>Again in Page 10. he ſaith, here is a great Cry, and a little Wool: A ſcoffer indeed. And in Page 7 he ſaith: <hi>I give my Glaſs a Rub, and that to the Purpoſe too, as I think</hi> (ſaith he) and thus ſcoffingly he writes theſe, and many more like them not worth anſwering, which I do Return upon his own head, who ſits in the ſeat of the Scorner, for it is plain, he writes one thing, and meanes another, which ſhews a <hi>Tongue without a Bridle,</hi> and his work to be with <hi>two Faces;</hi> and by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which he calls <hi>his Rule,</hi> is he found in the vain Religion. My laſt Teſtimony it needed no Rubbing; for I here teſtifie again, it is clear Truth, and clear enough to manifeſt the Deceit of him, and thoſe concerned with him in it; and it is here offered again for him, with other hypocrites, to ſee their <hi>Faces</hi> in, and alſo to the unbyaſſed mind, and to anſwer both his pieces of Envy, Lyes, Scoffs and Mocks; and were I not conſtrained for the Light and Truths ſake, I ſhould rather chuſe Silence, then to Anſwer either of his pieces of dirt, which at beſt is but Food for the Serpent, and his Seed to feed upon.</p>
                  <p>Again in Page 9. he accuſes me, <hi>with being a lewd Ranter in Dayes paſt.</hi> Now behold his Envy? for I have believ'd in the Light of Chriſt, and have been called a <hi>Quaker</hi> about <hi>Seventeen</hi> or <hi>Eighteen Years,</hi> and known to my Neighbours from my Childhood, which is above Fifty Years, and therefore the leſs Anſwer may ſerve this Man's Envy, who is a fierce Accuſer, and a worſe Judge; and my anſwer is by Way of Challenge to him and all his Abettors in Envy, <hi>To prove in Dayes paſt any
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99793:7"/>thing againſt me more then the fooliſh Courſe of the World, which the Men thereof (through Profeſſion) take a Liberty in, yet ſhort of bodily <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, Murder, and ſuch like groſs Enormities:</hi> but if I had been as bad as he renders me, and worſe alſo, to wit, <hi>If ſeven Devils,</hi> Mary Magdalene's <hi>State, had been my Condition, why ſhould his Eye or any Man's be evil, becauſe the Lords is good? She loveth much, becauſe much was forgiven her.</hi> And now from ſenſible Experience to our own Souls, we can teſtifie for God, That his tender Mercies is over all his Works, and reaches to the end of the Earth, &amp; follows Man calling to him in his vile Eſtate, yea, in the high-Wayes and Hedges, when the <hi>proud Phariſaical Profeſſor</hi> refuſeth the Wedding-Dinner, though bidden and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited, as this <hi>Nights Watch-Man</hi> with many more, have been, and have done.</p>
                  <p>Then he goes on in his former Manner in battering againſt his own raiſed up Bulwark, <hi>ſaying, I contradicted my ſelf in the Relation of</hi> Nicholas Woodman, <hi>in Page</hi> 9. becauſe I ſaid, <hi>Many were baptized by</hi> William Kiffin. This is not Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction at all to my ſaying, Nicholas Woodman <hi>was the firſt</hi> Baptiſt-<hi>Preacher raiſed up in the County of</hi> Kent, and ſo I ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, for they are my Words in my Book, to which I refer the Reader; and then Judge, who is the <hi>Two-Fac'd Man,</hi> and a <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verter of Words,</hi> and compare my Teſtimony to his, and then judge, whether he hath anſwered ſinglely, or may not be juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called, <hi>a Watchman of the Night,</hi> by his vailing of himſelf with his Night-Garments, under a Hood with <hi>two Faces,</hi> and then Harlot like wipe his Mouth, as if all were well, and lays his Lyes to my Charge, of which I could make a large Bundle; and of ſlanderous Aſperſions and ſcoffing Language, which his untimely Birth is filled with, I have been ſhort, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the large Advantage I might and could have taken, as for Lyes I can prove at leaſt <hi>Six or Seven</hi> more, then I have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered unto.</p>
                  <p>And then his ſlanderous Words of Woodman's <hi>being my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and plucking out mine own Bowels to beſmier them:</hi> as for <hi>Wood<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> an,</hi> I de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d him in Time paſt, before I leſt the Carnal <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> and their Carnal Worſhip, and beggerly Elements,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99793:8"/>which he continued in long after, preaching up and down: ſo no Brother of mine, but theirs, Root and Branch. And as for the <hi>plucking out of my Bowels</hi> (an Inhuman or Unchriſtian like Word) <hi>to beſmeer them,</hi> in ſaying, <hi>That he was the firſt</hi> Baptiſt <hi>Preacher raiſed up in the County of</hi> Kent; for they were my Words, which I ſtill affirm for Truth, though by this <hi>Night-watch-Man</hi> Perverted into another Sence; now wherein are they beſmeered by me, by calling him their Root, more then they have fouled themſelves by continuing in his foot-ſteps? only in this they differ, he was for the <hi>Particular Election,</hi> and they for the <hi>General,</hi> as more at large may be ſeen in my <hi>Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Glaſs.</hi> And as for my being a lewd Ranter as he ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly and maliciouſly accuſes me, if it were true, as its noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly falſe, that would not now help his bad cauſe; for what ſaith the Apoſtle? ſuch were ſome of you, <hi>but now ye are waſh'd,</hi> but <hi>ye are ſanctified, and you who were ſometimes Darkneſs, are now Light in the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. Yet this blind Watch-Man thinks in his dark Heart, that his accuſing me for Time paſt, for want of preſent matter to accuſe me now of, or ever ſince I have been call'd a <hi>Quaker,</hi> will help his bad and dark Cauſe and Phariſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Profeſſion, or crying out, I thank thee <hi>O Father, that I am not as this Publican is, or once was, &amp;c</hi>— Tedious would it be to anſwer all at large; but this day is this Scripture, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.21, 22. fulfilled upon this Mocker, <hi>God is a doing of his Work, his ſtrange Work, and bringing to paſs his Act, yea his ſtrange Act; now therefore be ye not Mockers, leſt your Bands be made ſtrong.</hi> And all whoſe Eyes are in their Head, may clearly ſee this Man's Bands of Darkneſs made ſtrong indeed, that dares ſo Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly Preach and Print againſt the Life and Light of Chriſt Jeſus, and this is all he hath to cover himſelf with, and Hole this Fox hath to creep into (to wit) in calling it the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers <hi>Erroneous Light, and the Dark Light of the</hi> Quakers; but that Cover is too narrow to hide him under, and that Bed is too ſhort to ſtretch himſelf on, and will be ſo found in the Day of the Lord, when his Blaſphemy ſhall be charg'd upon his own Head.</p>
                  <p>But now I ſhall return to his three Particulars in pag. 1. to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99793:8"/>prove <hi>C. B.</hi> in Fellowſhip with the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and led by their Spirit; ſaith he, Firſt, Bayly <hi>Propheſied, ſaw falſe Viſions, and pretended to Miracles:</hi> 2dly, <hi>He was then in Fellowſhip with the</hi> Quakers: 3dly, <hi>He was led by their Spirit.</hi> Now if his laſt be falſe, as it is, on which his whole Building depends, and by the Truth being removed, then muſt all his Work and Labour fall, as dirt caſt into a Dunghil: And that his laſt is falſe, take this Anſwer as followeth, Chriſt Jeſus propheſied, <hi>That falſe Prophets ſhould ariſe, and deceive many;</hi> who transform themſelves into many things like the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, to deceive (as their Father the Devil did) thoſe whoſe Minds are outward, yea, and if poſſible the very Elect, whoſe Minds are inward: yet who dare charge the true Apoſtles to be led by the ſame Spirit the falſe were? except <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael</hi>'s Off ſpring, and the falſe Prophets under the Law, <hi>that ſtole their words from their Neighbours, and they ran and propheſied, when the Lord never ſent them, and therefore they profitted not the People:</hi> yet we do not read of any but Blaſphemers againſt God ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe as this <hi>Night-Watch-man</hi> is, to charge the true Prophets Spirit with the falſe Prophets Preſumption, and Wickedneſs, as he doth the Light of Chriſt, our Principle, with <hi>C. B</hi>'s Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption and Wick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dneſs. And then again, Antichriſt the Man of Sin he ſits in the Temple of God, and ſaith, <hi>that he is God;</hi> and under the Name of Chriſt doth work in the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Iniquity, and ſo doth great Evils under the Name of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> as this day we ſee <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> full of Abomination, by which it is become as a Wilderneſs for Beaſts of Prey to live in; now is it kind Dealing with the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to charge them to be led by the ſpirit of Antichriſt, becauſe he pretends to the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pirit which the true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are led by? Nay, would not this <hi>Watch man</hi> think himſelf wronged to be ſo charged? yea ſurely; but if he were, yet were he not ſo much wronged as we are by his charging our Principle with <hi>C. B</hi>'s ſpirit, and the Effects thereof; for if our Fellowſhip ſtood only in outward and bodily Exerciſe, as the Fellowſhip of Water-dipping, and <hi>Chriſtendom</hi>'s Fellowſhip by Sprinkling doth, then might our Principle be the eaſier charged with his ſpirit; but becauſe our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99793:9"/>Principle, the Light, the Grace, the Word of the inviſible God is that, in which our Fellowſhip ſtands with God in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Truth; therefore not to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> judged by the Practice of Evil Men: and this (to wit) their Carnal Fellowſhip is the cauſe of their thus Oppoſing, Gain ſaying and Blaſpheming againſt the Light of Chriſt, which, whoſoever walketh therein, hath Fellowſhip with God, and one with another. And this <hi>Night-Watch-man</hi> ſaith, <hi>If this</hi> (to wit) Bayly<hi>'s Actions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> be not a Proof of</hi> Bayly <hi>being in Fellowſhip with the</hi> Quakers, <hi>then he knows not what is:</hi> and here I believe him, that our Fellowſhip he knows not, no more then <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> at large doth; and in this his Ignorance muſt we leave him, till he can believe in the Light, which will give him to ſee and know, wherein our Fellowſhip ſtands.</p>
                  <p>Another Proof that C. B. <hi>was in Fellowſhip with the</hi> Quakers <hi>he had, becauſe ſome joyned with him in Prayer, and heard him Preach, and one fell on the Ground, which is now none of the ſmalleſt</hi> Quakers <hi>in</hi> Dover ſaith this Accuſer: All this proves not the Matter, no more then the Weakneſs of a Young Child can p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ove the Strength of a Strong Man; and now, is it Reaſonable to judge the Principle of the <hi>Quakers</hi> by the Actions of them which were but juſt then as it were convinced, and being very young and tender (as I ſaid before in my <hi>Looking-Glaſs for the Baptiſts</hi>) they could not eaſily diſcern, and were afraid to judge: And now, to judge the Principle and Fellowſhip by ſuch, ſurely, amongſt Wiſe Men this will be counted Folly, and condemned for Prejudice.</p>
                  <p>And in pag. 9. he ſaith, <hi>If</hi> Duke Howard <hi>had proved by ſome convincing Arguments, that the</hi> Quakers <hi>Light is Chriſt</hi> as he Scof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fingly calls it) <hi>and then made it appear, that the</hi> Baptiſts <hi>had Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed in denying that Men are Redeemed and juſtified by that L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ght within themſelves. and not rather by Faith in the Death, the Reſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Aſcenſion of Chriſt without us, for us, which is the ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ef Point in Controverſie between us</hi> (ſaith this Oppoſer of Chriſt, the Life and Light of Men) and ſo indeed it is: and now that I have in my firſt Anſwer proved, and in this ſecond alſo, that Chriſt is the true Light, which lighted every Man that comes into the World, is as clear as the Sun: But ſaith this Scoffer
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99793:9"/>at the Light, that if he had prov'd, <hi>that the</hi> Quakers <hi>Light is Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> as if the <hi>Quakers</hi> Light, and the true Light that lighteth eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that cometh into the World, were two; here we affirm to all the World, that we never ſpoke of any other Light in us, but that which all Men are lighted with, even Chriſt, a Light to lighten the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and the Glory of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and if this Chriſt, the Light, Life, Wiſdom and Power of God be not in us Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning and Ruling, we are Reprobate, as well as others, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the whole currant of Scripture, which is the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hid from the Rebellious in all Ages and Generations, but in all the Obedient, <hi>Chriſt within the Hope of Glory; and Chriſt in you except you be Reprobates,</hi> ſaid <hi>Paul;</hi> and this is our Light, wherein our Fellowſhip ſtands with God, and one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and this all are Ignorant of, who make it their Buſineſs to Gainſay him in his ſecond Appearance, in the Light and Spirit, in which we are to know him to our Souls Salvation, if ever we be ſaved from Sin by him.</p>
                  <p>And now what is written in the holy Scripture concerning Chriſt Jeſus, his Birth, Sufferings, Death, Reſurrection and Aſcenſion, we do believe as much as any men living, and ſo I do believe <hi>Paul</hi> did, who ſaid; <hi>Henceforth know we him no more.</hi> It is alſo ſaid by <hi>John, He that confeſſeth that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the Fleſh, is born of God.</hi> Do not the <hi>Papiſts, Proteſtants,</hi> and all Sects, yea, even Drunkards and Lyars, that are ſhut out of the Kingdom, and all called <hi>Chriſtians</hi> confeſs to the truth of God's manifeſting himſelf in the Body of Jeſus, which he had prepared to do the Will in, even from the Birth to the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion: But will or dares any man ſay, that thoſe are born of God, becauſe all thoſe confeſs God manifeſted himſelf in Fleſh? and this Faith is as much as this <hi>Night-Watch-man</hi> pleadeth for, or doth believe of Chriſt in point of Juſtification, as his own words witneſs againſt him, ſaying, <hi>But rather in Chriſt without us, for us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To which I anſwer by living Experience, That Chriſt Jeſus, who offer'd up his Body through the Eternal Spirit, and pour'd out his Soul unto Death, and taſted Death for every man, thoſe his Sufferings have a living Extent unto every one that doth believe, and feel the Power by which he laid down that Body,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99793:10"/>and took it up again; and theſe are they, unto whom he becomes a Saviour from Sin, and gives them an Inheritance into Glory: and thoſe which believe only the offering up of the Body, and feel not that eternal Power to ſave from Sin, made manifeſt to them in his ſpiritual hight, cannot have a real Senſe and Feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Benefit of his Death, whatſoever they may pretend to of Faith in his Blood, neither can they have Salvation to their Souls: and this is my Anſwer, as a Teſtimony to the true Faith and Chriſt of God, a Quickning Spirit, the ſame ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday, to day, and forever, who was Glorified with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before the World began, from Everlaſting to Everlaſting, the Rock of Ages, and ſo <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Rock, which they drunk of; for they drunk of the Rock which follow'd them, which Rock was Chriſt, the Foundation of all the Generations of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in all Ages, <hi>Chriſt within the Hope of Glory; Chriſt within, except you be Reprobate; I in them, and they in me. that they may be one as we are one,</hi> ſaid Chriſt Jeſus the Light of Men: <hi>If any Man be in Chriſt, he is a New Creature:</hi> behold all things are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come new, new Heart, new Mind, new Will and new Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; the old Heart in the Earth, the new Heart is given to God; the old Mind Carnal, the new Mind Spiritual; the old Will Unſanctified, the new Will Sanctified; the old Affections in the Earth, the new Affections ſet upon things above; the old Converſation is after the Courſe of this World, which lieth in Wickedneſs; the new Converſation is in Heaven, where Chriſt fitteth at the Right hand of God: he that can read, let him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand.</p>
                  <p>And now to his Appeal <hi>to the Inhabitants and Magiſtrates of</hi> Dover, <hi>if I be not a falſe Man,</hi> as he ſaith, for my ſaying, <hi>They creep into Holes in a Day of Perſecution, and that our Rock is not as their Rock, our Enemies themſelves being Judges.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Reader, I have ſpoken the Truth, and I ſay it here again; and I appeal to the Inhabitants of <hi>Dover, Mayor</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> alſo, unto their own Conſciences likewiſe, whether I have wronged them in this at all? It is true, they were in their Meeting-place interrupted as all were that diſſented from the Publick, and their Meeting-Houſe Door was locked up by the <hi>Mayor</hi>'s Order, and then they, or ſome one for them knocked off the Lock, &amp; caſt it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99793:10"/>the <hi>Mayor</hi>'s Porch, as if they were valiant Men, as the Valiants of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and intended to meet again in their own hired Place; but whether ſo, or in Deſpight, there lies the Queſtion; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, they never met there more, till the King gave a general Liberty, as I ſaid before in the <hi>Looking-Glaſs</hi> to ſee themſelves in: <hi>But we ſtill met</hi> (ſaid this boaſter) <hi>elſe-where;</hi> it is true, they did meet; but where? I ſaid, <hi>In Corners:</hi> for which Saying he would make me a Lyar, and appeal to the Inhabitants and Rulers to be Judge, after a very confident Manner, in ſo falſe a Matter. And now let all the Inhabitants of <hi>Dover</hi> be judge, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they did not meet ſo private in Corners, <hi>ſince it was hard for people to know either Time or Place, and with ſo much Secrecy, that it was ſometimes at one part, and ſometimes at another part of the Town, and ſometimes in the Country, and one while by Five or Six in the Morning, and another while in the Evening, and at ſeveral un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain Hours of the day:</hi> Now whether I have wronged them in ſaying, <hi>they met in Corners,</hi> let the Inhabitants of <hi>Dover</hi> judge; for this is a true Relation, known well to themſelves, and others alſo. Now it was evident, and known to all, that we called <hi>Quakers</hi> alwayes kept our Meeting-Place, the Day and Hour; and their Practice of ſhifting Time and Place in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Privacies, that they might not be known when, nor where, <hi>was laid hard to us, by way of Perſwaſion to do the like,</hi> by ſome much concern'd, who were willing, that both themſelves and we might be ſaved from Damage; but we could neither change Time nor Place; and this was our Teſtimony to all concerned, who had Experience of them and us by an Impriſonment in <hi>Dover</hi> Caſtle before that time, wherein they did but add to our Bands; for they were ſoon gotten out (either directly, or indirectly) by Money given to the then Martial <hi>John Slowman;</hi> which becauſe we could not do for Conſcience ſake, we were born upon much the harder; <hi>and Sixteen Moneths, except Four Dayes, were we kept as it were Cloſe Priſoners, in a Room called, the</hi> Houſe of Office, <hi>with no Chimney in it, until the Governour</hi> Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Vincent <hi>got an Order from the King to ſit us free:</hi> and this was that he Scoffingly ſpeaks of, <hi>my ſeeing through the Stone Walls of</hi> Dover <hi>Caſtle;</hi> where he with others might have been, <hi>if their Cauſe had been good, and they true Men unto it,</hi> and then he need
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99793:11"/>not a mocked at my ſeeing through tee Stone Walls; and this Experience, with others of the like Nature, the Rulers and People of <hi>Dover</hi> had of them and us.</p>
                  <p>And thus I have run through ſome part of this <hi>Night-Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s Work, and confounded his vain Boaſting, and my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is Clear, and not Seared, as he Enviouſly ſeems to charge me; and here I ſhall leave him, and his dark mind and ſpirit an abſolute <hi>Night-Watch man, Scoffer</hi> and <hi>Scorner,</hi> and proceed to my Teſtimony to the true Light.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="testimony">
                  <head>A True Teſtimony to the Light and Power of Chriſt in the Heart.</head>
                  <p>ANd that is, that God is Light, and in him is no Darkneſs at all, and Chriſt is the Ligt of the World, and in him is Life, and his Life is the Light of Men; and to know, God and Chriſt is Eternal Life; and this Life is in the Son, and he that hath the Son hath Life, and be that hath not the Son; hath not Life. Now that which is to be known of God (and of this Eternal Life) is manifeſted in Man, for he hath ſhew'd it unto Man, even the Manifeſtation of the Spirit of Truth, which is given to every Man to profit withall, as a Talent or Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Knowledge of the Will of God concerning Man, of his State and Condition, as he ſtands in the Fall (by Sin having fallen ſhort of the Glory of God) is given of God unto Man, ſo hath he commanded the Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs, and hath ſhin'd into our Hearts, to give us the Light of the Knowledge of the Glory of God again in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt, to wit the Knowledge of the Grace and Truth, the Fulneſs of which dwelt in that Body which the Father had prepared, and this Grace and Truth which Man had depriv'd himſelf of, ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Darkneſs, has the Lord in Love to loſt Man made appear again by the Name of the Grace of God appearing to all Men, and Light ſhining in the Heart, where the Darkneſs and the Power thereof hath taken Place; ſo now the Grace of God
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99793:11"/>which brings Salvation, hath appeared unto all Men, <hi>teaching us</hi> (to wit, all that believe in it) <hi>to deny <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs and worldly Luſts, and to live ſoberly and Godlikely in this preſent evil World.</hi> Now the Grace that brings Salvation to as many as believe in it, is the Condemnation of thoſe which believe not in it; for this is the Condemnation, <hi>that Light (Grace) is come, and Men love Darkneſs</hi> rather then Light, becauſe their Deeds are evil: Light ſhineth in the Heart, by it the Lord doth ſearch out the deſperate Wickedneſs thereof, and ſo trieth the Reins, that all Men are left without Excuſe in his Sight: the Talent is given to all, Light ſhines in all, Grace and Truth appears to all, the Poſſeſſion of the Glory of God again is tendered to all through the Light which ſhines in the Heart, to give the Knowledge of the Glory of God again in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt, who is God's Power to ſave from Sin, and the power of Darkneſs and Death, which rules more or leſs in the Hearts of all the Children of Diſobedience to the Light, and thoſe be they that rebel againſt the Light, they know not the Way thereof, neither do they abide in the Path thereof; for to him that believes, it is a Path ſhining more and more unto the perfect Day, and in it doth the Lord meet with Man; thou meeteſt him that rejoyceth and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Righteouſneſs in thy Way; and he that is the Light of men, is the Way to the Father; and he that knows him, knows the Father alſo, for he reveals the Glory, <hi>which none of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this World by their earthly Wiſdom can come to behold, or ever could; but we behold his Glory,</hi> ſay they, <hi>which had believ'd in the Light, and</hi> were Children of it, <hi>which by the wiſe Men were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Accurſed, and that they knew not the Law;</hi> and ſo it is now, <hi>To you it is given to know the Myſteries of the Kingdom of Heaven; but to others in Parables;</hi> To you which believe in the Light, and ſo receive the Power to walk in it, and know the Way of it, the Juſt Man's Path, which is a ſhining Light, and rebels not againſt it; <hi>To you is the Father become a Fountain unſealed; to you i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Wel-ſpring of eternal Life opened; to you is the Power given t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ec-me the Sons of God; now are we the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on of God; but it doth not ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ppear what we ſhall be; now can we call God Father, and cry to bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iving Senſe of his b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>getting Power for dayly Bread, that we may be ſtrengthened with might in the inward Man, and that his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99793:12"/>Kingdom may come; which comes not by Obſervation, as lo here, and lo there; neither doth it ſtand in Words; but in Power, and conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of Righteouſneſs, Peace and Joy in the holy Spirit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that you may have Fellowſhip with us, herein is the Travel of our Souls, and that you may know him whom the Father hath given to be a Leader and a Commander to all that receive him <hi>the Light</hi> and <hi>quickning Spirit,</hi> and him that hath this Hope, purifies himſelf as God is pure, and hath the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in himſelf by his continuing, believing and Walking in the Light, where the Spring of Eternal Power is witneſſed <hi>to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Sons of God without Rebuke,</hi> and <hi>now if we walk in the Light as he is in the Light, then have we Fellowſhip one with another</hi> (mark that) <hi>and the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son cleanſeth us from all Sins;</hi> and this is the Fellowſhip which the Saints in Light have with God, in the Church which is in God, and one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>by one Baptiſm, which is our entrance, by the one Spirit, into the one Body, of which Chriſt Jeſus is the Head, World without end.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this is a Plain, Faithfull and True Teſtimony born through living Experience to the true Light of Chriſt Jeſus, which we in ſcorn called <hi>Quakers</hi> believe in, and declare of to all men in the Love of God, and of no other, ſaith</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Luke Howard.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="questions_for_Hobbs">
                  <head>Here followeth a few <hi>Queries</hi> for this <hi>Night-Watch-man</hi> to Anſwer according to Scripture, before ever he be by his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſearched out the third time, and found again, as he hath twice been already, a raking in the Bottomleſs Pit to fetch up Matter againſt the Light of Chriſt Jeſus.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. VVHether the Light of Jeſus be not the Light of Men, and a Meaſure of the Spirit of Truth given to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man, as a Talent to profit withal? and whether it doth not convince the World of Sin, of Righteouſneſs and of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and is not the Condemnation of all that believe not in it, ſeeing that the Condemnation is, <hi>that Light is come into the World, and men love Darkneſs rather then Light, becauſe their Deeds are evil?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:99793:12"/>
                  <p n="2">II. Whether ever we called <hi>Quakers</hi> ever declared of, or te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified to any other Light, then that which <hi>John</hi> called, <hi>the true Light, which lighteth every man that cometh into the World;</hi> we ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Paul, <hi>That God hath ſhined into our Hearts with it, to give us the Light of the Knowledge of the Glory of God, in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and if we, or any People elſe believe not in it, then is<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t not the Condemnation of all ſuch? but if we do believe in it, we have the Witneſs in our ſelves, even the Light &amp; Life accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Scriptures, which we do believe are to be fulfilled?</p>
                  <p n="3">III. Whether all that oppoſe the Light in the Heart, be not Oppoſers of the Life of Jeſus, ſeeing that <hi>in him is Life, and his Life is the Light of Men?</hi> and whether all that gain-ſay and oppoſe this Light of Jeſus, be not Fighters againſt God, and Blaſphemers againſt his Temple, and the Worſhippers therein, and ſo have no part of the Inheritance with Saints in Light?</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. What is the Word in the Heart, that Man may hear it, and do it? and what is that Word which is ſaid to be the Name of Chriſt Jeſus (the Power and Wiſdom of God) by which Word we may come to know him, who is from Everlaſting to Everlaſting, the ſame yeſterday, to day, and forever?</p>
                  <p n="5">V. What is the Manifeſtation of the Spirit, which is given to every man to profit withal, if it be not the Light within? and what is the Light, which lighteth every Man, if it be not the Light within? and what is the <hi>Quakers</hi> Light, if it be not that which every Man is lighted with, ſeeing thou makeſt a Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, crying out, <hi>The Quakers Light,</hi> and <hi>Wo be to him that walks by the Dark Light of the</hi> Quakers?</p>
                  <p n="6">VI. What is the Grace of God, and where doth it appear, which brings Salvation, that hath appeared unto all Men [mark] <hi>unto all men,</hi> if it be not the Light of Chriſt in the Heart? and whether th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Quakers</hi> have not a ſhare in that Common Grace, as well as others, ſeeing it is to all Men? then what difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Quakers Light,</hi> and <hi>all mens,</hi> in the firſt Gift to man?</p>
                  <p n="7">VII. What is that Leaven which the Woman took, and hid in three Meaſures of Meal, until the whole was leavened? and what is the Grain of Muſtard-Seed, which a Man took and ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his Field, the leaſt of all Grains, and grows the greateſt of all Hearbs? and what are the Fowls of the Air, which lodge in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99793:13"/>the Branches of it? And what is the Pearl hid in the Field? and what, and where is the Field? and who is the Merchant Man? and what is that he parts with for the Field? and how, and with what doth he dig deep to find the Pearl? And what is the Groat the Woman loſt and found again, when ſhe had ſweeped her Houſe? and what is the Houſe and Broom, with which ſhe ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped? And what is that Talent the Houſholder gave to his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and then himſelf went into a far Country for a time, and then at his return again called them to an Account? And what is the Draw-Net caſt into the Sea? and what is the Sea? and what are the Fiſh? and what is the Veſſel and the Good Fiſh that are put therein, and the Bad Piſh that are caſt away?</p>
                  <p n="8">VIII. What is that Baptiſm that is to remain ſeeing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, there is <hi>one Lord, one Faith, and one Baptiſm:</hi> is it <hi>Johns,</hi> or is it <hi>Chriſts?</hi> or is it <hi>Water,</hi> or is it <hi>Spirit?</hi> or muſt there be <hi>two?</hi> And what is that true <hi>Bread</hi> which comes down from God, the fleſh of Chriſt which he gives for the Life of the World? <hi>and whether he that eats of, it ſhall not live for ever; and whether any have Life, but thoſe that eat thereof;</hi> and whether your Bread be that yea or nay, which you give each other as an <hi>Ordinance</hi> of God, as you call it?</p>
                  <p n="9">IX. What Baptiſm is that now <hi>which gives an Entrance into the one Body of which Chriſt Jeſus is the Head,</hi> ſeeing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Truth which we believe and own, ſay, <hi>That by one Spirit are we all baptized into the one Body?</hi> and who is the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrator of this Baptiſm? and when may it truly be ſaid of any Man, that he is baptized with this Baptiſm?</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Luke Howard.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:99793:13"/>
                  <p>A Looking-Glaſs FOR BAPTISTS Being A Short Narrative of their <hi>Root</hi> and <hi>Rice</hi> IN KENT.</p>
                  <p>Wherein the Erroneous Spirit of <hi>Richard Hobbs</hi> (Paſtor of the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> in <hi>Dover,</hi> with ſome others therein concern'd with him) is Reprehended.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By</hi> Luke Howard.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>Be ſober, be vigilant, becauſe your Adverſary the Devil, as a roaring Lyon, walketh about, ſeeking whom he may devour.</p>
                     <p>Whom reſiſt ſtedfaſt in the Faith, knowing that the ſame Afflictions are accompliſh'd in your Brethren that are in the World.</p>
                     <p>But the God of all Grace, who hath called us into his Eternal Glory by Jeſus Chriſt, aft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r that you have ſuffered a while, make you perfect, ſtabliſh, ſtrengthen ſettle you.</p>
                     <p>To him be Glory and Dominion for ever and ever, Amen,</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 Pet. chap. 5. verſ. 8, 9, 10, 11.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>Printed in the Year, 1673</p>
               </div>
               <div type="authors_note">
                  <pb facs="tcp:99793:14"/>
                  <p>THis <hi>Narrative</hi> is for the <hi>Unbyaſſed Minds</hi> to look into, whether <hi>Baptiſts</hi> or others: in which ſhort <hi>Narrative</hi> (by all ſuch) may be ſeen the <hi>Rice</hi> and <hi>Root</hi> of the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the Face of an Envious ſpirit ruling in <hi>Richard Hobbs,</hi> Paſtor of the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> in <hi>Dover,</hi> as he pretends himſelf to be, with all concerned with him in it (except he has beguil'd any) to ſet their Names to an Envious Story of one <hi>Charles Bayley,</hi> Ten Years by paſt; to which Story there is Nine Names, but five of them dead for ſeveral Years; and <hi>C.B.</hi> of whom the Story is, was by the <hi>Quakers</hi> deny'd ten Years ſince, and ſo is to this Day, as in this <hi>Narrative</hi> will appear to the <hi>Authors</hi> ſhame, becauſe they have known he was deny'd for ſeveral years, as their own <hi>Conſciences</hi> will teſtifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
                  <p>This they joyn'd to another like it ſelf, at the Re-prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it, which before was ſufficiently Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Forgery therein detected to all unbyaſſed Minds.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:99793:14"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>READER,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Hearing of, and this day ſeeing a Scandalous Narrative from the <hi>Baptiſt</hi>-People of <hi>Dover,</hi> at the reading of which I could not but very much ſtrange, that men ſhould ſo much loſe their Reaſon, as men, that as ſoon as they have a little Liberty given them, to abuſe it ſo, as to imploy themſelves in ſuch dirty work once and again of Nine and Ten Years by paſt, and ſo to make themſelves a Scorn to Fools, and the innocent Principle of the <hi>Quakers</hi> the Worlds Talk, whom they hate, as <hi>Ahab</hi> did <hi>Micaiah;</hi> and therefore is their work like themſelves, whoſe Envy deſtroys their Reaſon, which is the Cauſe they Print ſuch things as are filled with Miſchiefs, and no good to any; though ſuch as envy and hate the Light of Jeſus, and perfect Way of the Lord (and ſo bring not their deeds to it) may rejoyce thereat. The tendency of which Narrative was of <hi>C. Baily</hi>'s ſpirit and works manifeſted in <hi>Dover</hi> in the 8th Month, call'd <hi>October,</hi> 1661. to crown the reſt of their work in their other Narrative (to which this of <hi>C. B.</hi> was added in the Reprinting of the ſame) as the Baptiſts in ſubtilty thought, or might think. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was ſomething upon me to give forth a true Relation (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my knowledge) of <hi>C.B.</hi> and his being denyed long ſince by us, and ſo not to be by Wiſe Men accounted of us.</p>
                  <p>And alſo, for the Truth's ſake, to make a ſure Diſcovery of the Rice of the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent</hi> (who ſhew what ſpirit they are of by their works in Print) that they ſhould not be lifted up, and glory in the fleſh above their ſphere, and ſo preach and affirm they know not what unto the people, which are more ſimple (<hi>ſome of them</hi>) and cleaner in heart and mind, before they are Dipped, then ever they come to be again, <hi>after once they are proſelited into their Yoak of Bondage;</hi> and therefore is this plain Diſcourſe (for the Simple ſake) given forth.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>The 9th day of the 5th Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, called</hi> July, 1672</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>L. H.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:99793:15"/>
                  <head>A LOOKING-GLASS for Baptiſts, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>IN the Year 1643. and 1644. the People call'd <hi>Baptiſts</hi> began to have an entrance into <hi>Kent;</hi> and <hi>Anne Stevens</hi> of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> (who was afterwards my Wife) being the firſt that received them there, was dipped into the Belief and Church of <hi>W. Kiffin,</hi> who then was of the Opinion commonly called, The particular Election and Reprobation of Perſons; and by him was alſo dipped <hi>Nicholas Woodman</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> my ſelf, and <hi>Mark Elfreth</hi> of <hi>Dover,</hi> with many more both Men and Women, who were all of the Opinion of the particular Point, and who reckoned themſelves of the Seven Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in that Day, who gave forth a Book call'd, <hi>The Faith of the Seven Churchs;</hi> which was then oppoſit to the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> that held the general (and is ſtill the ſame) at which time there was great conteſt betwixt thoſe <hi>Baptiſts</hi> called, <hi>The General,</hi> as <hi>Lamb, Barber,</hi> and thoſe which held the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Love of God to all;</hi> and <hi>Kiffen, Patience, Spillman</hi> and <hi>Colyer,</hi> and thoſe that held the <hi>Particular Election;</hi> ſo that if any of the particular Men or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the <hi>Seven Churches</hi> aforeſaid, did change in their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the <hi>Particular</hi> to the <hi>General,</hi> that then they were to be <hi>baptized</hi> again, <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>You were baptized into a wrong Faith, and ſo into another Goſpel,</hi> uſing that ſaying, <hi>That if any man bring any other Goſpel, then that which we have received, let him he accurſed;</hi> whereupon ſeveral denied their <hi>Belief</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and were baptized again into the <hi>General Opinion or Belief:</hi> But <hi>N. Woodman</hi> aforeſaid, with <hi>M. Elfreth,</hi> with all of then in <hi>Kent</hi> (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Daniel Con</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> which never baptized any) held their <hi>Baptiſm</hi> in the <hi>particular,</hi> but changed their <hi>Opinions</hi> to the <hi>General,</hi> &amp; ſome to <hi>Free-will,</hi> and the <hi>Mortality of the Soul,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other things too redious here to relate, from whence did ariſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99793:15"/>almoſt all the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> which now are in <hi>Kent,</hi> whoſe <hi>Root</hi> is <hi>Babel</hi> and <hi>Confuſion</hi> (which ſo much boaſt themſelves in this day of a little Calm) ſo that in their <hi>Root</hi> (to wit. <hi>Baptizing into the Faith of Particular Electioners</hi>) they being <hi>falſe,</hi> neither <hi>Branch</hi> nor <hi>Fruit</hi> can be <hi>true,</hi> but a <hi>confuſed Breed, Increaſe,</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> is the very beſt ſtate they can lay claim unto by their own Rules, if the General Opinion and Practice of <hi>Lamb</hi> and <hi>Barber</hi> be true, of whoſe Opinion theſe <hi>Baptiſts</hi> in <hi>Kent</hi> profeſs now to be of, (though they did ariſe from the <hi>particular Root</hi>) and devoutly preach't it up, as if they were Naturaliz'd into the <hi>Root</hi> of the <hi>General,</hi> by Baptiſm: and ſo make Proſelites to themſelves in that which they know not whereof they do affirm, not being <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually Baptiz'd into the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Love of God;</hi> and ſo you Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of this People cauſe them to err, and they that are led by you are deſtroyed (for <hi>where the Blind lead the Blind all muſt needs fall into the Ditch</hi>) and when they are proſelited to hold <hi>Truth</hi> in <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eouſneſs,</hi> they are made two-fold more the <hi>Children of Hell</hi> then they were before, becauſe they are now covered with a <hi>Profeſſion</hi> without <hi>Life,</hi> which <hi>God's Spirit</hi> leads not to, but <hi>mans Traditions,</hi> as before proved by their <hi>falſe Baptiſm:</hi> And here many ſimple Ones think themſelves in their ſtate to be <hi>Rich</hi> and <hi>Full,</hi> becauſe they can now ſay ſomething for their <hi>Opinion,</hi> as they have leavned of their <hi>Leaders,</hi> when as they are <hi>Poor, Blind</hi> and <hi>Naked,</hi> and as <hi>empty</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> to <hi>lead</hi> as ever they were in dayes paſt, and as ignorant of the One Lord and <hi>One Baptiſm</hi> by <hi>One Spirit,</hi> into the <hi>One Body,</hi> whereof <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> is the <hi>Head,</hi> as ever they were, becauſe the <hi>Root</hi> and <hi>Foundation</hi> of their <hi>ſtanding</hi> is <hi>rotten,</hi> and laid in <hi>Babel</hi> and <hi>Confuſion;</hi> and all this appears ſufficiently unto thoſe whoſe Eyes are opened by the <hi>Eye-ſalve</hi> of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> who counſels all to buy of him <hi>Eye-ſalve,</hi> that they may <hi>ſee</hi> (to wit) themſelves in the <hi>Fall,</hi> and him who is the Light a Quickening Spirit to <hi>redeem</hi> up to God, out of the Fall; and all ſuch behold and underſtand things which dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, and can ſee the <hi>Ground</hi> and <hi>Root</hi> of you, and of the Bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which remains in you Carnal <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> againſt the Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eatance and <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and the Truth profeſſed in it by the People of God called <hi>Quakers.</hi> Oh! the height
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99793:16"/>of <hi>Enmity,</hi> and Abomination of <hi>Cruelty,</hi> which lodgeth in the <hi>Hearts</hi> of ſome of your <hi>proud Leaders,</hi> who call the <hi>Scripture</hi> their Rule, and yet walk ſo <hi>contrary</hi> to it; for doth it not ſay, <hi>Do unto all Men as you would they ſhould do unto you?</hi> which in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things you do not; as in your <hi>Printing</hi> and <hi>Publiſhing Forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> and <hi>Falſhoods,</hi> and the <hi>Miſcarriages</hi> of ſome who never were eſtabliſhed amongſt us; but ſince denied by us: do you not hereby ſeek to caſt <hi>Dirt</hi> upon us all in your <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> as if it were a thing of <hi>yeſterday,</hi> and allowed of by us at this time? Cannot you ſee your <hi>Envy</hi> and great <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> in this thing? For do not you know who are the <hi>Authors</hi> of that <hi>Story,</hi> that it is about <hi>Ten Years ago,</hi> that <hi>Charles Baily</hi> was a Priſoner in <hi>Dover?</hi> And do not you know in your <hi>own Conſciences,</hi> that he hath been by us, call'd <hi>Quakers,</hi> deny'd for <hi>many Years?</hi> And is he not then to us as a <hi>Stranger</hi> or <hi>Heathen man,</hi> according to the <hi>Scriptures?</hi> And what is that in you, that lays his Miſcarriages to our Charge? now, is not that againſt the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> which you call your <hi>Rule?</hi> And beſides, you belye him too in ſome things, as bad as he was; and ſo you ſhew your <hi>ſpirit</hi> to all men, and eſpecially to the <hi>Wiſe in Heart,</hi> who will forever conclude you to be <hi>as you are,</hi> and that he is not to be accounted of us, nor his <hi>Actions</hi> laid to our <hi>Charge,</hi> as you <hi>envious People</hi> have done: you were <hi>moved</hi> to do it; but ſurely you were ſo <hi>moved</hi> in <hi>Envy,</hi> as were <hi>Joſephs</hi> Brethren, when they ſold him into <hi>Egypt</hi> (it was a <hi>Murdering Motion</hi> at the beſt of it) but God was with him to their <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Confuſion</hi> of <hi>Face</hi> in due time, and ſo is he with us: and I do believe, though you do not <hi>now Bluſh,</hi> yet you <hi>ſhall Bluſh</hi> and be <hi>Aſhamed,</hi> when the <hi>Fruits</hi> of your own <hi>doings</hi> ſhall <hi>correct</hi> your <hi>Folly:</hi> For what have you to <hi>glory</hi> in, but your own <hi>Shame?</hi> If we ſhould look back among your <hi>Society,</hi> as you deſerve what might be ſaid, as many of you well know, and ſome pretended <hi>Leaders</hi> too, <hi>Thou that ſaith, another ſhould not Steal, doſt thou Steal?</hi> here read your <hi>ſelves:</hi> but for the ſake of the Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple I ſhall not here inlarge, yet ſuffer a little to be ſaid concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>N. Woodman</hi> aforeſaid, who was the firſt <hi>Baptiſt-Preacher</hi> and <hi>Dipper</hi> reared up in this <hi>County</hi> of <hi>Kent,</hi> from whence your <hi>Rice</hi> is, whoſe <hi>Evils</hi> I will not lay to the <hi>charge</hi> of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconcerned</hi> in this matter; but to ſpeak a little to inform you, which know not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99793:16"/>your <hi>Root</hi> and <hi>Rice,</hi> which before is call'd <hi>Babel</hi> and <hi>Confuſion,</hi> and <hi>rotten;</hi> and now judge your ſelves if it were not ſo; for there be many yet living, which know the <hi>Truth</hi> of this following Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and much more.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Woodman</hi> took to <hi>Wife</hi> and honeſt ſober <hi>widdow Woman</hi> in <hi>Dover,</hi> named <hi>Katherine Brown,</hi> who lived in good faſhion in the Town, and for his <hi>Profeſſion's ſake</hi> married him, who in <hi>idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> ſpent her <hi>Means,</hi> and then abuſed her <hi>Body</hi> with many <hi>Blows;</hi> when he had her in the <hi>wide Fields</hi> in the <hi>Wilde</hi> of <hi>Kent,</hi> then would he leave her there to ſhift for her ſelf, and himſelf go from Place to Place to preach up <hi>Water-baptiſm;</hi> of whoſe (with more ſince his time) <hi>filthy</hi> unheard of <hi>Abominations,</hi> both in <hi>ſpirit</hi> and <hi>practice,</hi> there might be more ſaid then you can ſay of <hi>C. Baily,</hi> as ſome of your ſelves well know, which we are not willing to relate in <hi>Print,</hi> except provoked to it by your here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after <hi>Carriages.</hi> Now, <hi>C. Baily</hi> we are as clear of, as we are of you in the ſight of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Wiſe Men,</hi> and as clear as the <hi>Churches</hi> were of them denied by them in the <hi>Primitive Times,</hi> of which the <hi>Scripture</hi> is a full <hi>Witneſs</hi> for us, and againſt you in this <hi>Caſe,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your great <hi>ſhame</hi> in putting forth this your <hi>Folly</hi> in <hi>Print</hi> of Ten Years conceivings.</p>
                  <p>Now this Man, your <hi>Root,</hi> and from whence you <hi>roſe,</hi> was not in his day inferior to any of you, <hi>in preaching the Scripture words without Life,</hi> as you do, and <hi>in getting Diſciples to him,</hi> as you do; but his <hi>Folly</hi> was made <hi>manifeſt,</hi> as yours in <hi>due time</hi> will alſo be, who through <hi>feigned words</hi> deceive the Hearts of the Simple, and make them two fold more the <hi>Children of Hell,</hi> then they were before they came amongſt you, as ſaid Chriſt Jeſus to the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,</hi> in whoſe <hi>ſteps</hi> you are found, with the <hi>Sheep's Clothing,</hi> but in the <hi>Wolves Nature,</hi> inwardly <hi>ravening;</hi> and ſo your Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs doth not exceed theirs, becauſe the <hi>Ravening</hi> and <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Nature</hi> is ſtanding in you, as in them, which can look <hi>ſeven, eight,</hi> or <hi>ten</hi> years backward, to ſmite with the <hi>Fiſt of Wickedneſs,</hi> and <hi>perſecute</hi> the <hi>Innocent</hi> with your <hi>Tongues</hi> for want of power in your <hi>Hands</hi> to effect your <hi>Wills,</hi> whoſe <hi>Opinions</hi> we well know, and much more then is here ſaid; and what is here ſaid, is not there a cauſe for it? let the Unbyaſſed in Heart and Mind judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in the Caſe, and let the Lord judge, who
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99793:17"/>judgeth not as man in the <hi>Fall</hi> judgeth, but will judge <hi>Righteous Judgement.</hi> But to return, Now this Man your <hi>Root</hi> is gone, and many which knew him not are gotten into his <hi>Form,</hi> cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up your <hi>Water-Baptiſm</hi> as the Jews did <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and a <hi>Temple,</hi> with other things, which God commanded in its Day, as was <hi>Baptiſm</hi> to John, which was to decreaſe; but the <hi>one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> of Chriſt by the <hi>one Spirit</hi> into the <hi>one Body</hi> was to increaſe, as <hi>John</hi> teſtified of him, and ſtands a <hi>Witneſs</hi> in the <hi>Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> againſt you all. And ſo we ſay, <hi>There is one Lord, one Faith,</hi> and <hi>one Baptiſm</hi> to be <hi>contended for,</hi> and to be <hi>lived in,</hi> by all who are of the <hi>Church</hi> which is <hi>in God,</hi> of which <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> is the <hi>Head,</hi> World without end, when all things which are ſeen ſhall have an End.</p>
                  <p>And this Teſtimony lives in my Heart for God. That it is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> nor not <hi>Baptiſm</hi> in <hi>Water,</hi> that availeth any thing no more then <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> but a <hi>New Creature</hi> (here read your<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelves) <hi>and as many as walk according to this Rule</hi> (to wit, <hi>of the New Creature</hi>) <hi>Peace be unto them, and to the whole Iſrael of God;</hi> and now Wiſdom is juſtified of her <hi>Children,</hi> and every <hi>Tree</hi> is known by its <hi>Fruit,</hi> &amp; ſo are you to all, whoſe Eyes are open to ſee your <hi>Folly</hi> and <hi>Envy,</hi> in raking <hi>Ten Years</hi> back, as if you had ſate <hi>brood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the <hi>Cockatrice Egg</hi> all this time, to <hi>hatch</hi> forth the <hi>Serpent's Seed</hi> of <hi>Envy,</hi> to come behind, and <hi>bruiſe</hi> the <hi>Heel</hi> of an <hi>Innocent People,</hi> which have deny'd, and do deny (and all along our <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple</hi> hath been againſt) ſuch ſpirits as <hi>C. Bayly</hi>'s was of <hi>Ten Years</hi> ſince, and is of now. But <hi>Richard Hobbs,</hi> who takes to himſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>f the name of <hi>Paſtor of the</hi> Baptiſts <hi>in</hi> Dover, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th in p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 7. of their <hi>Hatcht up Envy, That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f the</hi> Quaker<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>ſhould de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Charles Bayly <hi>to be owned a very eminent Man amongſt them at the time of his Impriſonment, that then they will render themſelv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that ever profeſſed Religion.</hi> Thus, <hi>Capera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lts himſelf, as it he ſpoke <hi>Truth,</hi> and knew all the <hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                           <desc>•••••</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> Minds at that time; but his <hi>Anger</hi> over-ruli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g his <hi>Knowledge</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to ſeek of his <hi>Proof,</hi> although he ſeems to prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t by his com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>on Lords Day after,</hi> as he ſaith, <hi>to the Priſon, and there ſaw</hi> C. B. <hi>and moſt of the</hi> Quakers <hi>in Town with him; and he Pray'd, and ſome of them kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> A <hi>poor Proof:</hi> He there neglects relating, That ſeveral of he <hi>Men Friends</hi> were then <hi>Priſoners</hi> in <hi>Dover</hi> Caſtle; and beſides,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99793:17"/>amongſt them at <hi>Liberty</hi> there were ſome which did not own <hi>C. Bayley</hi> ſo much as <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> reporteth of, though to him it was not declared; and beſides, <hi>Anne Howard</hi> my Wife (I being then a <hi>Priſoner</hi> in the Caſtle) did ſo far diſown him, that ſhe ſent up to <hi>London,</hi> to the Elders of Friends, and gave them an Account of his <hi>mad Actions,</hi> who ſent down <hi>two Friends</hi> to look after him, and they teſtified againſt him, when they ſaw him; this <hi>Friends</hi> did not acquaint the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> with, who we knew waited for <hi>Miſchief:</hi> but <hi>Friends Care</hi> was of him, to preſerve him, if poſſible, and to reſtore him in the <hi>Spirit of Meekneſs</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> as our <hi>Duty</hi> is according to Scripture; but when no <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery</hi> can be, then <hi>deny'd,</hi> as he was and is to this day. And how can be charge the <hi>Principle</hi> or <hi>Body</hi> of our <hi>Friends</hi> with him, ſave <hi>Envy</hi> it ſelf? And beſides, thoſe <hi>Friends</hi> which chiefly were with him in the <hi>Priſon</hi> were young <hi>Convinced,</hi> and <hi>tender,</hi> and could not eaſily diſcern, and afraid to judge, not knowing what to ſay; but to us in the <hi>Caſtle Priſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> when they came up to us, they would ſpeak as it was, but this did not we ſee meet to <hi>acquaint</hi> the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> with, but rather endeavoured to get him to <hi>London,</hi> which was done in order to his Recovery; ſo that Friends are clear of him in the ſight of God, and according to Scripture, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> in envy ſeek to lay <hi>Stumbling-blocks</hi> in the way of the <hi>Simple</hi> by it, &amp; ſo do tranſgreſs the <hi>Law of God,</hi> and <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> which they in <hi>words</hi> call <hi>their Rule,</hi> which ſay, <hi>Thou ſhalt not lay a Stumbling-Block in the way of the Blind, but ſhalt fear thy God:</hi> But they ſhew their <hi>Spirit</hi> to the <hi>full;</hi> and the Lord judge between us and them for his <hi>Seed's ſake.</hi> And ſurely if theſe men had been in the dayes of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> they would have done as the <hi>Jews</hi> did, <hi>lay blame to the Life and Doctrine of them, becauſe of Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages in</hi> Judas, <hi>and others,</hi> of which the <hi>Scripture</hi> declares much, and that through them the Name of God was <hi>blaſphemed;</hi> but ſurely the <hi>Blaſphemers</hi> were to bear their <hi>burden</hi> from the Lord, as well as the <hi>Cauſe-givers,</hi> and ſo muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all now; <hi>for the Lord will not be mocked, but as every one ſows ſo muſt he reap, even the fruits of their own doings;</hi> and ſo muſt you for all your <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> againſt the <hi>Light of Jeſus,</hi> which we declare of, <hi>which every man is lighted withal,</hi> according to the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> though you preſumpuouſly ſometimes call it <hi>Natural,</hi> and <hi>ſcoffingly</hi> and <hi>enviouſly, the Quakers dark Light,</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:99793:18"/>with many more <hi>blaſphemous words,</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> of old did, in whoſe <hi>ſteps</hi> you are found <hi>walking,</hi> and whoſe <hi>works</hi> you are found <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in the <hi>ſpirit of envy,</hi> which ſaid, <hi>This is the Heir, come let us kill him, that the Inheritance may be ours:</hi> now he that <hi>envyeth</hi> is a <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlayer</hi> or <hi>Murderer;</hi> and we know, <hi>that no Murderer hath Eternal Life abiding in him;</hi> and we may juſtly deſire of the Lord, <hi>to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from ſuch unreaſonable men, which ſo ſhew your Teeth, as very ready to bite, if you had but power;</hi> crying out in a <hi>publick Aſſembly</hi> of <hi>Baptiſts</hi> in <hi>Dover, That he which anſwered your falſe Accuſations of eight or mine years Envy, deſerv'd to have his Ears nail'd to the Pillory, for only his ſetting two Letters for his Name;</hi> which ſhews your <hi>ſpirit</hi> to all wiſe men ſufficiently: And therefore, let your <hi>Profeſſion</hi> be what it will, <hi>the body of death is ſtanding in you, in which the Perſecutor and Murderer lives,</hi> for how unlike a <hi>true Chriſtian</hi> are your <hi>works,</hi> in raking for <hi>matter</hi> ten years back, to beget in people an <hi>evil Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Quakers? and what will you get by it amongſt the wiſe in Heart</hi> but <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>contempt?</hi> for our <hi>Rock</hi> is not as your <hi>rock</hi> is, as late experience hath ſhown, our <hi>Enemies</hi> themſelves being <hi>Judges;</hi> and now you ſhew, what <hi>ſeed</hi> you are of, by biting at our <hi>Heels,</hi> and ſmiting us with the <hi>Fiſt</hi> of <hi>Wickedneſs,</hi> and perſecuting us with your <hi>Tongues</hi> for want of <hi>power,</hi> laying to our charge his <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> which we have deny'd <hi>ten years ago.</hi> O ye Fools! ſo ſoon as ever the King gives you a little <hi>Liberty</hi> to meet, where you were afraid of man to meet but a little time ſince, and ſo <hi>crept</hi> into <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ers;</hi> is this the glorious &amp; beautifulleſt <hi>Fruit</hi> you have to appear with? ſurely this is not the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> which is from <hi>Above,</hi> which is <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>irſt Pure, then Peaceable, and eaſie to be entreated;</hi> but that <hi>wiſdom</hi> which is from <hi>Beneath,</hi> where the <hi>Serpent's life</hi> is, which is <hi>earthly, ſenſual</hi> and <hi>deviliſh,</hi> which bites at the <hi>Heel: Surely Duſt is and ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e the Serpents meat, and upon his Belly ſhall he go all the days of his life:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere read your ſelves, if you can underſtand what it means, ſaith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e who is a true <hi>Friend</hi> to all mens <hi>Eternal Peace,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dover, <date>
                           <hi>the</hi> 9th <hi>day of the</hi> 5th <hi>Moneth,</hi> 1672.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Luke Howard.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="postscript">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:99793:18"/>
                  <head>A Poſtſcript.</head>
                  <p>This <hi>Baptiſt</hi> Paſtor, and as many of his Flock as are of his mind, would have all people to believe, <hi>That the ſpirit by which</hi> C. B. <hi>was acted, when he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d err'd in his heart from God, was and is the ſpirit, by which all the <hi>Quakers</hi> are led by, as the very Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of their Religion.</hi> This is the thing which his printing is for, to poſſeſs people with a Belief of; and he thinks in his Serpent's Wiſdom, that he hath made it ſure enough in ſaying, That he was owned an eminent <hi>Quaker</hi> at the time of his Impriſenment, and running out, to which I have Anſwered already, how he was then looked upon by Friends, whom he reputes to be a Poor, Miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>led and Deluded People; but in that Way which he accounts Deluſion, to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. Believing in the Light of Jeſus, which ſhines in the Heart and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> manifeſt in every mans Conſcience, do we worſhip God in, even in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>it and in the Truth, which the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilis out of, and all which do his works of Envy: And therefore ſomething is yet in my Heart to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſpirit of Envy in the Baptiſt Paſtor (as he ſtiles himſelf) and that on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wiſe.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt Jeſus was glorified with the Father before the World was, and in time manifeſted to the World in that Body, which the Father had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared him to do his Will in, whoſe Name is call'd, <hi>the Word of God,</hi> by which the World was made, who took upon him the Seed of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> and declar'd to be the Son of <hi>David</hi> according to the Fleſh but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Son of God according to the Spirit, by the Reſurrection from the dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: who had all Power in Heaven and Earth given to him, by which he gave Commiſſion to his Apoſtles or Meſſengers, to Baptize into the Name of the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, which is into the Nature and Life of each, which is one divine Nature; and theſe three being one in Nature and Beeing and every one which is herein baptized, knows the Father and the Son b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Spirit, which to know is eternal Life, which is to increaſe in which they alſo know <hi>John</hi>'s Miniſtry and Baptiſm, which was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, elſe there muſt be two perpetual Baptiſms; but there is one Lord, one Faith, and one Baptiſm, which is to be contended for, and lived in by all who are of the true Church, which is in God the Father of Spirits, and of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> the Quickning Spirit,
<pb facs="tcp:99793:19"/>the Lord from Heaven, who in his Body prepared him to do the Will of God in, went up and down doing good, and choſe Twelve, and one of them was a Devil, not a Devil when he choſe him [Mark that] for when he had part of the Miniſtry, then a Servant of God, but he erred in his heart, and fell away, and it was ſaid, <hi>Let his Habitation be deſolate, and let no man dwell therein; and his Charge let another take:</hi> What now Baptiſt Paſtor? wouldſt thou not here have judged all, becauſe he walked and profeſſed among the reſt of the Diſciples? and yet afterwards in eating and drinking with them was called a Devil by him that had choſen him into his Service before, in which he had ſo walked, that each Diſciple was ready to queſtion himſelf, <hi>Is it I?</hi> and <hi>Is it I?</hi> here would not thy ſpirit have ſaid, Ah! you are all alike, led by one ſpirit? here ſee thy ſpirit and face thou blind Paſtor. And <hi>Peter,</hi> he deny'd his Maſter. and curſed and ſwore he knew him not; would not thy envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us ſpirit have ſaid, Ah! they are all alike, and led by one ſpirit, for all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hey have been a preaching up the Light? yet would not thy Phariſaical <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pirit have condemned all for <hi>Peter?</hi> and though he found a place of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, what is that to thee and thy judgment againſt the Truth in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſe? for <hi>Judas</hi> found no more place, then <hi>C. B</hi> hath yet found; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et he had a part, and might be, and was reckoned a Diſciple, as well by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he reſt of the Diſciples as <hi>C. B.</hi> was reckened a <hi>Quaker</hi> by ſome of the <hi>Quakers;</hi> for to ſome he was manifeſt, as I ſaid before, though you <hi>Baptiſts</hi> knew is not. And then <hi>Demas,</hi> he forſook <hi>Paul,</hi> and embraced <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he preſent World; what wouldſt thou have ſaid leſs then, Ah! they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll alike, led by one ſpirit, let them profeſs what they will? for thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hich ſaid, the Apoſtles turn'd a the World up-ſide down, and contradicted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd blaſphemed their Doctrine: What do you <hi>Baptiſts</hi> in this your Work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iffer from them? And thoſe which had the Form, and not the Power, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hich were to be turned away from; what would thy <hi>Jewiſh ſpirit</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ave ſaid, <hi>Ah! they are all alike, led by one ſpirit, for they ſpeak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>like and act alike?</hi> as this blind Paſtor ſaid, <hi>Charles Baily did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſt as the</hi> Quakers <hi>in all things, both in Words and Actions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>herefore all one ſpirit,</hi> ſaid he. And then <hi>John</hi> ſaid, <hi>They went <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut from us, becauſe they were not of us, that it might be made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>anifeſt, they were not all of Us:</hi> He doth not ſay, <hi>They had never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>een among them [Mark that]</hi> but, <hi>They were not of them:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere wouldſt not thou have been the <hi>Accuſer of the Brethren,</hi> and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nvy have been ready to have <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rinted againſt them,</hi> and have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aked
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:99793:19"/>
                     <hi>Ten Years</hi> back to have proved them that <hi>went out from them to have been of them, at ſuch a time, and at ſuch a time,</hi> and eſpecially <hi>at that time when they held out their Golden Cup of Profeſſion in good words,</hi> as you do? Here may you ſee your ſelves, <hi>if the God of this World hath not blinded your Eyes.</hi> And then in the Churches there was ſome Fault found with the moſt of them in ſome things; if thou <hi>Paſtor</hi> of <hi>Dover-Baptiſts</hi> hadſt been in thoſe dayes, and heard of it, would not this thy ſpirit have ſaid, <hi>It is all their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and one ſpirit leads them all?</hi> as thou doſt ſay concerning the <hi>Quakers,</hi> againſt whom thou <hi>watcheſt for Evil both in words and action, and then bringſt it forth Ten Years after it is done,</hi> ſo much out of Time, that it was high time it had been <hi>buried long ſince,</hi> that it might have been <hi>rotten before now;</hi> but now to Print ſuch long-paſt things, ſhews thy ſpirit and thy ſelf to be but a <hi>Woolf in the Sheep's Clothing,</hi> and ſo a <hi>very unfit Paſtor to over-look a Flock,</hi> and eſpecially the <hi>Flock of Chriſt,</hi> when thou art alwayes a <hi>ſnarling</hi> at our <hi>Heels,</hi> as the Serpent's Nature is, bringing back Blows of <hi>Ten Years</hi> old, and of that which we are no more to be charged with then the Saints of old, as before declared, might be with the falſe ſpirits, which were once amongſt them, and then went out into the World, as <hi>C. Baily</hi> is gone. Now all had a beginning of the Work in themſelves, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they went out from the Church, and at the firſt appearance of that ſpirits working in the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtery of Iniquity, and transforming of it ſelf as an Angel of L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ght; for to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udge a whole Body and Church of People to be all led by that ſpirit, is not this to be the Accuſer of the Brethren, and eſpecially, when that people deny &amp; teſtifie againſt that ſpirit in due time, as you Baptiſts know in your own Conſcience we have done? is not this Wickedneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and Env<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> drunk in by you, as an Ox drinks in Water? and ſurel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, if you had not made your ſelves drunk with the Whore's Cup of Abominations, you muſt needs have been Wiſer Men; but having drank deep, the dreggs ſo ſtick in your Throats, that makes you thus vomit up your own ſhame, and that Nature nothing will clenſe you of ſhort of the <hi>Divine Name of Chriſt Jeſus, which leadeth to God;</hi> but you, in the Old Man's Nature and Envious Holineſs, can get the <hi>words</hi> to <hi>talk of,</hi> and <hi>profeſs</hi> in the <hi>Ravening Nature,</hi> fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ching up ſuch old Matter againſt the <hi>Quakers</hi> of <hi>Ten Years ſtanding,</hi> and Print it, as if People ſhould believe <hi>it were now our Principle, Spirit and Practice;</hi> againſt which, with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99793:20"/>the Paſtor and his Flock, which have a hand or conſent to it, we have a <hi>Teſtimony for the Lord</hi> to bare in the <hi>Truth,</hi> which is <hi>Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> our <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Life: For he that hath the Son, hath Life, and he that hath not the Son, hath not Life, he which hath the Son hath the Father alſo;</hi> unto whom be Everlaſting Praiſe.</p>
                  <p>And bleſſed are they, which are not offended in Chriſt Jeſus the Light of men, who is the Foundation that God has laid, and chief Corner-ſtone of this Age, as in Ages paſt, though the wiſe Maſter-builders refuſe now to build thereon, as the Generations of old did; but now is the Lord a taking of the Wiſe in their own Craftineſs, with the little Foxes, which deſtroy the Vineyard, from and by whom Offences come; but We be to them, by whom they come, becauſe, if they do not fall on this ſtone Chriſt Jeſus, and ſo be broken to pieces, it will certainly fall on them, and grind them to powder, when there ſhall be none to deliver: Therefore the Wiſe in Heart will prize their time, whilſt it is called to day, and whilſt they have the Light to believe in it, that ſo they may be the Children of it, leſt darkneſs comes upon them, and ſo their feet ſtumble upon the dark Mountains even at noon day; for Light was in <hi>Goſhen,</hi> when Darkneſs was and is in <hi>Egypt,</hi> even ſuch darkneſs as may be felt of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually ſo called, where our Lord was and is Crucified; he that can read, let him underſtand, and prize his day, and live to God, and not to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; that ſo in all things God may he glorified in all, and through all, and over all, who is Bleſſed forever and forever, <hi>Amen.</hi> ſaith</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>The 14th of the 5th Moneth. 1672.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline> 
                     <signed>Luke Howard.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:99793:20"/>
                  <p>THE Water-Baptiſts Reproach REPELD.</p>
                  <p>Being A further <hi>REPLY</hi> Anſwering a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> to his pretended <hi>Impartial Narrative</hi> of one <hi>C. Bayly,</hi> hereto a pretended <hi>Quaker:</hi> A Story of 11 years ſtanding. IN Defence of an <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the ſaid <hi>Narrative;</hi> clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the People call'd <hi>Quakers</hi> of the <hi>Water-Baptiſt's</hi> Calumny and Abuſe blabbed out againſt them.</p>
                  <p>By T. R.</p>
                  <p>Printed in the Year, 1673.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:99793:21"/>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:99793:21"/>
                  <head>TO THE Impartial Reader.</head>
                  <p>HAving lately read a Pamphlet (whoſe <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to his <hi>Reader</hi> is ſubſcribed <hi>Richard Hobbs</hi>) weighed the Arguments, and conſider'd the Tendency of that Diſcourſe; I could do no leſs then write a few Lines as reaſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ble Remarks upon it. The Piece is aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Author to be a <hi>Sober Reply</hi> to <hi>Luke Howard:</hi> which had the Author perform'd, he neither had thus abuſed thee, nor occaſion'd me this Trouble. And truly, Reader, I muſt tell thee, I have not often met with more Impertinency, or Abuſe wrapt up in ſo ſmall a Fardle; which confirms me, that the Promiſe of a <hi>Sober Reply</hi> in the Front of his Pamphlet was to <hi>Gild the Poyſon-Pill, to ſwallow the more glib;</hi> without which Artifice (I doubt not but) he's ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently ſenſible the Palate of this Age would not eaſily touch, much leſs take his Potion.</p>
                  <p>How conſiderable <hi>Richard Hobbs</hi> is amongſt his Brethren, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine not; but as a <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>acher,</hi> and <hi>Water dipper</hi> at <hi>Dover</hi> amongſt them of his Perſwaſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n he is exerciſed, and has been for ſome years paſt, and writ a Supplement to a ſtrange <hi>Prodigy,</hi> or <hi>Miracle,</hi> pretended to be wrought by his brother <hi>R. James,</hi> a Preaching <hi>Dipper,</hi> or <hi>Water-Baptiſt</hi> in <hi>Lincolnſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The firſt piece of Abuſe (I mean that out of <hi>Lincolo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſhire</hi>) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the World with a Miracle, and I muſt ſay, a ſtrange one too, a <hi>Leproſie</hi> and diſeaſed Family miraculouſly cured by them, whoſe known and owned Belief, and Principle are, that <hi>Miracles are ceaſed:</hi> which exceeds the very Power of Chriſt's Apoſtles, that could not ſo much as cure the <hi>Lunatick</hi> having not Faith, <hi>Mat. 17.16, 17.</hi> And gain, that they ſhould he ſo kind to a <hi>Quaker,</hi> and his Family, as to cure them, whom of all Perſons they hate, and which of all Perſons (they ſay) have not Faith; is beyond all Bounds of Romance. And this uſher'd in as a late piece of <hi>ſtrange Providence,</hi> and <hi>Finger of Heaven</hi> of few days, or weeks ſtanding before publication; although the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:99793:22"/>
                     <hi>Cheat</hi> was Eight or Nine, ſome ſay Twelve Years paſt acted by thoſe <hi>Water-Baptiſts,</hi> and now brought to light to their Shame, and their <hi>Sophiſtry</hi> diſcovered by <hi>W. S.</hi> in Anſwer to <hi>Ralph James</hi> his <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfuge, &amp;c.</hi> to which I refer the Enquirer. But to return to <hi>R. H.</hi> whoſe <hi>Sober piece</hi> (as he would inſinuate it to be) I have now under hand, and ſhall (as a Friendly <hi>Reader,</hi> to whom he directs his Defence of a pretended <hi>Narrative</hi> formerly publiſh'd concerning <hi>Charles Bayly</hi> ſometimes a Priſoner in <hi>Dover</hi>) make ſuch reaſonable Remarks and Obſervations, as may give thee to underſtand the Author's Drift and Depth in his former, and renewed appearing in Print againſt us, and by which the Impartial and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nprejudiced may judge, Whether it be a <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ply,</hi> or an <hi>Envious Retort</hi> to his <hi>Opponent?</hi> whether writ in Love, or in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>roach? whether in ſolid and ſound Judgment, or an airy and corrupt Mina? And I affirm, the Matter will beſt diſcover, of what ſpirit the Author is; <hi>for the Tree is known by its Fruit.</hi> Yet its not my purpoſe to charge his Diſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>genuity upon all that may bear that Name (for there are loſt Sheep, whoſe Innocency and Simplicity is betrayed by ſuch as <hi>He,</hi> who cauſe them to err, whoſe State and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I really pitty, and deſire their Recovery) But with much Plainneſs to deal with him, who Brawles in our Streets, and utters a Reproach at our Gates, of and from which a though in the Sight of God and good Men we are clear, and innocent; yet for the ſake of the Simple, and all ſuch, with whom any Doubts of us may yet remain, is this as a <hi>Seaſonable Caution,</hi> that in the ſight of all <hi>Truth</hi> may be clear, and the <hi>Slander</hi> may lie at the <hi>Fool's Gate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>London,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>1673.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline> 
                     <signed>T. R.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:99793:22"/>
                  <head>THE Water-Baptiſt's Reproach REPELD, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>THis <hi>Water-Baptiſt,</hi> that he might appear a <hi>Methodical</hi> Writer, preſents his Reader with an Epiſtle, as a <hi>Key</hi> to open the Secrets of his ſucceeding <hi>Diſcourſe.</hi> But that they are of the leaſt Allyance each to other in that ſenſe, I cannot find; but <hi>both</hi> being wrought with Envy, and Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; they may paſs with a <hi>probatum eſt</hi> for <hi>Companions.</hi> Its ſome difficulty to determine, whether the Zeal of our Author run him more into the former; or latter? but certainly he may claim a conſiderable ſhare of either. And if his <hi>Proſelites,</hi> whom he paſſes through his Watery <hi>Element,</hi> be no better clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from their <hi>Confuſion</hi> and Filthineſs, then his Lines of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie; he might better ſpare his Pains, and they their Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. 'Tis poſſible, <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> preſuming the Impreſs paſſing the hands of the Water-Criticks, or Book-Readers of the Town, might change its ill ſhaped Dreſs, and preſent it <hi>more refined</hi> to the World; ſo ſpared a Review of his ſeven or eight Moneths Pains. Yet I'le not ſet ſo little by our Author, but own to all that he barks, which may be Argument enough for Approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'s fit to go out.</p>
                  <p>In his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> he thus treats his Reader, viz. <hi>I do here preſent thee with a ſma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l Tract, containing a brief Reply to a Book put forth by</hi> Luk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Howard, <hi>intitul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d,</hi> A Looking-Glaſs for the Baptiſts; <hi>The Contents of which Book and the Intents of the Author is to obſcure the Truth of the Narrative, which is hereunto annexed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt I anſwer, <hi>R Hobbs</hi> has not here dealt candidly with me, and his Reader, referring us to an annexed <hi>Narrative,</hi> when there's not one Section, Chapter, or Particular in all his ſucceeding Diſcourſe, or any Piece annexed, that imports
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:99793:23"/>any ſuch Matter: ſo that the Cauſe of his Cavil cannot be eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly examined, he not ſhewing us what he cavils at; an Abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, had it been by us, would have been baited to purpoſe. Yet that I may afford our Adverſaries that Aſſiſtance and Supple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they ever denyed us, I have traced back the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and am willing to allow him the help of any <hi>Narrative</hi> formerly printed, ſo far as it may clear the Truth, of what's in <hi>Controverſie</hi> betwixt us.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Then firſt, I find that in the <hi>Re-printed Pamphlet</hi> relating to the <hi>Lincolnſhire Prodigy,</hi> there's a ſupplemental Letter, and a pretended true and <hi>impartial Relation</hi> of ſome remarkable Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of <hi>Charles Bayly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for the <hi>Letter,</hi> it bears date from <hi>Dover, June</hi> 10. 1672. by a Nameleſs <hi>Author,</hi> and without any Accompt <hi>to whom ſent:</hi> ſtuft full of Calumny, and Reproach, attended with ſuch Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, as might well excuſe the naming either the Forger or Foſterer thereof; however its <hi>Tincture</hi> and <hi>Complection</hi> may well diſcover who <hi>writ it;</hi> and ſhould <hi>Richard Hobbs</hi> deny to father it, and caſt it upon ſome or other of his Brethren, as did his Brother <hi>Ralph James,</hi> when charged with that notorious Lye (in the Front of his Pamphlet of Eye and Ear Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of that pretended Miracle wrought upon the Leper by his and his Brethren's Prayers) who ſaid, <hi>it was none of his Compoſing;</hi> yet its Language would betray it: <note place="margin">See his <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfuge,</hi> p. 13. See pag. 9.</note> (and a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Circumſtance, <hi>Luke Howard</hi> has charged it upon him, which <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> denies not by his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply) not much differing from that Dialect in which his pretended true Relation is penned. And then</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Relation relates to <hi>C Bayly;</hi> who, ſay they, acted ſeveral things as a <hi>Quaker</hi> from the 13th of <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tob.</hi> to the 22th, 1667. (which really was in 1661.) which the Forgers would charge upon all called by that Name, which is the Cauſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie betwixt <hi>Luke Howard</hi> and <hi>R. Hobbs,</hi> the firſt clearing, the 2d caſting all the Dirt of <hi>Charle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſe cringe upon us; which <hi>R. Hobbs terms</hi> in <hi>L. Howard</hi> obſcuring the <hi>Truth</hi> of the <hi>Narrative.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that the Impartial Reader may have a juſt Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding whether <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> or <hi>L. Howard</hi> has been Malicious and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99793:23"/>Clamarous uttering a Reproach and Slander, cavilling againſt the Truth, and abuſing his Reader; I ſhall deſcend in theſe few Particulars to evince to the impartial Underſtanding: and ſhall go on
<list>
                        <item>I. To manifeſt the nullity of the <hi>Water-Baptiſts Charge</hi> by his <hi>Letter</hi> and <hi>Relation.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>II Our Clearneſs from its Impoſitions.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>But previous hereto I would have the <hi>Reader</hi> take notice, that its neither my Work, nor Purpoſe to vindicate <hi>C. B.</hi> (whoſe <hi>Miſcarriages</hi> long ſince ſeparated him from us, and againſt whom our Teſtimony was many years paſt given out for his <hi>Diſobedience</hi> to that everlaſting Light and Truth of God: for the Sake of which Truth <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> is ſo <hi>inraged</hi> againſt us) But to clear the Truth, and the faithfull Followers of Chriſt from the wretched Impoſitions and calumnious Impoſtures of our Malitious Adverſaries. Then</p>
                  <p n="1">I. The Nullity of <hi>Water-Baptiſts Charge</hi> appears in theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Its own <hi>Contradictions,</hi> and moſt apparent and palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble falſneſs.</item>
                     <item>2. His averring thoſe things, that abſolute neceſſary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence doth contradict and deny. Which if prov'd, will be no hard Matter to determine, Whether <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> his <hi>Evidence</hi> in this matter be ſufficient to <hi>prove</hi> us guilty of his <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lumny</hi> and <hi>Reproach?</hi> for which I need to go no further, then <hi>R. Hobbs,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting and charging <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> by his <hi>Letter</hi> and <hi>Narrative</hi> in Print</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>R. Hobbs,</hi> that <hi>C. Bayly</hi>'s Miſcarriages might<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly upon us, and upon that Truth of God we bear Witneſs unto, he affirms in his ſaid Letter (Pag. 17) that <hi>C. Bayly</hi> did thoſe <hi>Actions</hi> at the ſame Time, when he was owned by us as a very eminent Man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, yea, ſays he, "After he had acted theſe things in the "Narrative, they did own him as aforeſaid. Here's the <hi>Accuſers Charge,</hi> from which he would evince all <hi>call'd Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> to be guilty of his <hi>Miſcarriage.</hi> And to prove his Poſition, he lays down this onely Argument, and none other, viz. As appears by this (ſays he) <hi>One Lords day, after this Tragedy was paſt, I came to viſit my Brethren in Priſon, and went into</hi> C. Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly's
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:99793:24"/>
                     <hi>Chamber to reaſon with him: in which Time came in moſt of the</hi> Quakers <hi>of the Town,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See the Letter dated <hi>June</hi> 10. 1672.</note> 
                     <hi>with whom</hi> Bayly <hi>went to Prayer, and divers of them I obſerv'd fall down upon their Knees in that Duty; my ſelf, and three more Bap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iſts ſtav'd in the Chamber all the while he was in Prayer: in which Praye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> I very well remember he ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly bagg'd of God, that he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>la ſend his A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gel, and bind me Hand and Foot, and caſt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>mo Chains of Darkneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> Thus would he prove, <hi>Co. Bayly</hi> was owned after his Miſcarriages, as divers joyning with him in Prayer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> As for moſt of the <hi>Quakers</hi> of the Town coming there, or joyning in Prayer in ſuch manner, as he deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and falſly inſinuates, is after in its place anſwer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d and refeld: but as to the <hi>Time</hi> inſtanced when this was pretended, I further ſay, <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> forgetting the Method his pretended <hi>Impartial Relation</hi> was penn'd in, or his Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al out-running this Policy in the very Front of thoſe his remarkable Paſſages gives us this very Story in the firſt Paragraph of thoſe recorded Actions, <note place="margin">See Pag. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; <hi>2.</hi> of the Relation.</note> and there rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tes that <hi>C. Bayly</hi> fell to praying, &amp;c. (relating that Paſſage) O Lord God of my Life ſend down thine Angels and bind this thine Enemy Hand and Foot, for he (meaning <hi>R. Hobbs</hi>) hath oppoſed and reſiſted thy pure Spirit, &amp;c. So that what is pretended to be laſt in his Letter, is firſt in his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Relation.</p>
                  <p>But ſhould it be objected, That this Piece of Remark was ill plac'd in the Hiſtory, and might be an after Paſſage, though firſt related here.</p>
                  <p>Anſw. That is not probable, for the 2d Story following this of the Prayer begins thus, <hi>About two Dayes after,</hi> &amp;c. (rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting plainly to the Time of the former Story) And follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that begins another Paragraph thus, <hi>Within a ſhort Time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> &amp;c And ending the whole Relation with a Story of <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tob.</hi> 22th, 1667. ſo that <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> his onely Proof of <hi>C. Bayly</hi> being own'd by the <hi>Quakers,</hi> after his acting thoſe Paſſages in the Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative abſolutely falls to the Ground without the leaſt Colour or Pretence of Truth, if the pretended Hiſtorical Impartial Relation be in the leaſt to be credited. And to put all our of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:99793:24"/>doubt, with a moſt ſolemn aſſeveration that Hiſtory is thus cloſed, viz: This Relation we that ſubſcribe do teſtifie in the preſence of God is true: under which is printed no leſs then <hi>R. Hobbs,</hi> and the Names of eight perſons more.</p>
                  <p>And ſo if the Relation be true, the Letter is moſt horridly falſe; and whether to believe <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> in one, or <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> in the other, or <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> in either, I leave the Juditious Reader to Judge.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Another Paſſage obſervable in <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> his Letter is this: neer the Cloſe thereof to give his Reader a pregnant <hi>Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> of his <hi>Modeſty</hi> about the publiſhing the <hi>Relation,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>The only</hi> Reaſon why it was not publiſhed ſooner, was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſhould ſeem to ſome as if I had <hi>boaſted;</hi> And muſt <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> his Reader credit him in this? I muſt needs ſay, the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risee</hi> hath told a fair Tale to enforce a belief, that 'twas no ſmall ſhare of ſelf-denyal in him, that refuſed the proclaiming an inſtance of Providence, that would add ſo highly to his Praiſe. But alaſs! if <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> were guilty of any ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he moſt grandly miſtooke himſelf in a few Lines b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e, where (ſurmiſing that ſome Readers might Queſtion th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Relation or Honeſty of the Forgers to detain it in Obſcurity for ſo many Years before it came to Light) he excuſes himſelf and inſinuates to his Reader, that the Fault was not his: And ſaith <hi>R. Hobbs,</hi> If any queſtion, why it is publiſhed now, and not before, my Anſwer is this, I ſen a Coppy of it to a Friend in <hi>London</hi> ſome Time ago.</p>
                  <p>So that after this rational Acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mpt of his Innocency 'twere unreaſonable to charge <hi>R. H.</hi> for keeping this Story for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years for fear of his appearing to ſome, as if he had boaſted, as he gives for his only Reaſon, when he tells his Reader a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, how little he was acceſſary to its being ſo long kept in obſcurity, giving this further Reaſon for its Publication; <hi>I ſaw</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Truth of Chriſt might be advantaged thereby.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Further <hi>Inſtances</hi> not much leſs <hi>abſurd</hi> (in this Letter) might be brought to ſhew the intolerable Folly and Abuſe of this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Water-Baptiſt, whoſe bitter and malitious Spirit has led him thus to be a ſhame to his party, Abuſe to his Reader and Deriſion to juditious Men.</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:99793:25"/>
                  <p n="3">3. The next matter is the Printed Relation it ſelf, at the foot of which is written, <q>This Relation we that ſubſcribe do teſtifie in the Preſence of God is true, we being Eye and Ear Witneſſes of theſe things, ſome at one time, and ſome at another: <hi>Tho. Patridge, Simon Lovelace, John Heale, Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher Streeting, Thomas Williams, Richard Hobbs, John Hobbs, John Finnes, Edmund Finnes.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here's there joynt Aſſeveration or Proteſtation, that the Relation is true, every Particle thereof averred unto by no leſs then Nine Witneſſes; and this to credit thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Story concerning <hi>Charles Bayly;</hi> which whether true or falſe relates not to us: yet to manifeſt the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable Abuſe</hi> of its Forger, I ſhall remark his indirect Dealing with, and Impoſing upon his <hi>Reader.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. In preſenting the Relation under the hands of nine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as Witneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s thereto, yet in Fact five of them dead before the drawing up of the ſame: which <hi>L. Howard</hi> charges in p. 3. upon <hi>R. H.</hi> and has no Anſwer to i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and if that be not a full Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and Proof of that Piece of Abuſe, look but to <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> his foremention'd <hi>Letter</hi> from <hi>Dover</hi> of <hi>June</hi> 10. 1672 where he confirms the ſam in theſe words, <hi>and when</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>the Narrative was drawn, I ſhewed it to all the Perſons, that are now alive, who all own every Sentence in it.</hi> But whom alive, and whom dead, not a word: a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uble <hi>Abuſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. But 2dly, That which has a more Scarlet-dye, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Forgers of it moſt criminal, is, that under their hands each Perſon teſtifies to every Particular of the Relation, as each being an Eye and Ear Witneſs to every Paſſage, and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the <hi>Narrative.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here I muſt take notice, that its uſually obſerved, that the Judges (in Matter relating to <hi>meum &amp; tuum</hi>) in caſe a Witneſs teſtifies beyond the Bounds of his Knowledge in any one Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, do ſuſpect him for all; yea, and reject him as a Perſon not to be credited: and ſhall ſo many, and frequent Inſtances of Unconſcionable Abuſe be expoſed to the Eyes of our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; and yet the Expoſer ſtand with an untoucht Reputation? I leave it to the Impartial; and return to the Matter.</p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:99793:25"/>
                  <p>It had been Modeſt for theſe <hi>Water-Baptiſts</hi> to have teſtified; that ſome of them were Witneſs to <hi>one particular,</hi> &amp; ſome of them to <hi>another</hi> (as probably they might) &amp; not ſo audaciouſly to bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it by their bold, though unadviſed Aſſeveration: <hi>We (eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them) do teſtifie every Sentence in it to be true,</hi> and that in <hi>the Preſence of God:</hi> when 'twas <hi>impoſſible,</hi> that all could be privy to every <hi>Sentence,</hi> as the thing it ſelf fully demonſtrates. Its eaſie to reconcile, who made them to Err? viz<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> their <hi>Paſtor R. Hobbs,</hi> who ſpeaks the like Language in his Printed <hi>Letter</hi> of <hi>June</hi> 10. 1672. <hi>When the</hi> Narrative <hi>was drawn, I ſhewed it to all the Witneſſes that are now alive: who all own every Sentence to be true, and ſtill freſh in their Memories:</hi> when the greater number of them are dead, and none of them witneſs to one and the ſame Matter, as hereafter will appear.</p>
                  <p>Yea, but return to the <hi>Relation</hi> or <hi>Narrative</hi> it ſelf; and it preſents another Complexion: not all, nor one half of them witneſſing every Sentence; but clearly otherwiſe. To ſome Sentence no Witneſs, other one, others two or three: and ſo giving ſuch Teſtimony to the reſpective Parts, as then were ſaid to be preſent at the particular Action: as appears thus out of their own Relation or Narrative.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The firſt paragraph relates a Report of <hi>Charles Bayly</hi>'s coming from <hi>France,</hi> and the Noiſe of his coming to <hi>Dover,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See the Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive printed <hi>1672. pag. 19.</hi>
                     </note> and being taken from the <hi>Quakers</hi> Meeting. This was but a Report to the <hi>Water-Baptiſts</hi> Witneſſes, who then were in Priſon: and ſo they not Eye and Ear Witneſſes, as affirmed.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. After this Hiſtorical Diſcourſe is an Account of <hi>C. Bayly</hi>'s Preaching, <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> his Oppoſition, and <hi>C. Bayly</hi>'s Prayer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, that he might be bound hand and foot, &amp;c. And this Sentence cloſed without Witneſs (with an &amp;c.) and not one <hi>Water Baptiſt</hi> mentioned to be there, but R. H. much leſs all the pretended Eye and Ear Witneſſes. See p. 19, 20.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Nex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is a full Acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mpt of <hi>Charles Bayly's Prophecy</hi> (as there its termed) againſt <hi>R. Hobbs;</hi> in the Body of which Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Tho. Patridge</hi> is ſaid to be preſent with <hi>R. H.</hi> and not a Word
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:99793:26"/>of any other. Therefore to the foot of that <hi>Paragraph</hi> is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, 

<q>
                        <hi>Witneſs</hi> So but Two of the Nine Eye and Ear Witneſſes.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas Patridge,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Richard Hobbs.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Then followeth a Diſcourſe betwixt C. B. and R. H. where there is not the leaſt mention made of any of the many Eye and Ear Witneſſes to be then preſent; which Sentence ends thus: 

<q>
                        <hi>This, I teſtiſie, is true; witneſs my Hand,</hi> Richard Hobbs.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Certainly, <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> did much miſtake the Point, when he by his <hi>Letter</hi> confidently affirm'd, <hi>That all owned every Sentence to be true.</hi> But to proceed,</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The next Paragraph of the <hi>Narrative</hi> gives a further Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>R. Hobbs,</hi> and cloſed the Hiſtory of <hi>C. Bayly</hi>'s Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes againſt him, which mentions not more then Three to be preſent; and is witneſſed by <hi>Tho. Patridge, Edmond Finnes, John Hobbs;</hi> and had the reſt been there, we had without doubt heard of it.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. And laſtly the Relator gives us a large Story of a Conteſt 'twixt <hi>C. B.</hi> and one <hi>Wollett</hi> a man frenzie in his Brain, who took <hi>C. Bayly</hi> to be one of the <hi>Locuſts come out of the Bottomleſs Pit,</hi> becauſe of his Hair, &amp;c. where was preſent Five of the <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> as ſayes the Story, viz. <hi>T. Patridge, Ed. Finnes, Simon Lovelace, Jo. Hales</hi> and <hi>Chr. Streeting;</hi> not one word mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of their <hi>Paſtor,</hi> who uſually bore the greateſt part in the other <hi>Acts:</hi> or of the Three other writ under in the general Atteſtation. Yet ſayes <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> in his <hi>Letter, All averred every Sentence</hi> (and he himſelf ſubſcribed it) <hi>to be true:</hi> although ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them (as plainly demonſtrated) abſent, when ſeveral of there preſented Matters were acted; &amp; moſt of them dead, when the Relation drawn up: as appears largly by R. H's <hi>Letter</hi> and <hi>Narrative</hi> it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>Now therefore I recommend it to the Judicious and Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, of what Perſwaſion ſoever, to judge of R. H's Labours, whether they be the <hi>Product</hi> of Love, or Envy? of ſound Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,
<pb facs="tcp:99793:26"/>or a confuſed Mind? And whether he now brought his ſuper-annuated and confuſed Story to Light in order to clear the Truth, and Love to his Oppoſers, as he boldly inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuates; or rather as a Relique of that Enmity and Hatred, which the Wicked One has ſown in his Heart, from which his <hi>Water-Waſhing</hi> has not cleanſed him: and to the Witneſs of God in all I appeal.</p>
                  <p>Having waded through the Depths of <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> his unſtable Foundation, and vewed the irregularity of this <hi>Watery-Builder;</hi> let's now return to his latter piece of <hi>Architect,</hi> and examin, What Monuments he now raiſes upon the old Bottom.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Then firſt I obſerve, that in the Front of his Reply to encourage the Reader, who might ſuſpect his Cauſe (by reaſon of the confuſed witneſſing of the late Relation) he tells him, <hi>That the Truth of the Narrative is further evidenced.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon the view of this large Averment, I preſently turned over his whole piece, if poſſible to find him as good as his word; but alas; it was <hi>Labour loſt:</hi> for inſtead of producing freſh Witneſſes, and new Evidences, as he boldly inſinuates; he brings pregnant Inſtances of his old Abuſe, and that accompanied with an ill-favour'd way of <hi>Canting,</hi> which iſſues from him much like a <hi>Proverb</hi> out of a <hi>Fool</hi>'s <hi>Mouth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Then next, he proceeds to certifie the Reader, <hi>That the Narrative was not publiſhed to blemiſh the Perſons of the</hi> Quakers, <hi>nor yet from a Spirit of Envy,</hi> pag. 3. And truly, if <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> did expoſe his Fardle to the World in a Spirit of Love, and to advance the Reputation of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> I muſt acknowledge my Miſtake. And whether he did it not for the End he denieth; ſuch who weigh the Circumſtances following, may judge firſt of
<list>
                        <item>1. An old Story of ſo many years ſtanding now to be brought out in Print.</item>
                        <item>2. And of a Perſon, that ſince theſe Miſcarriages has never been owned amongſt us.</item>
                        <item>3. And to be accompanied with ſo many Inſtances of ſevere Reflections.</item>
                        <item>4. Backed with ſuch a number of apparent Contradictions and Falſities.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:99793:27"/>
                  <p>As the Proverb is, <hi>He that runs, may read;</hi> and needs not an Interpreter.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. But he tells us plainly, what his Quarrel is againſt, that <hi>if any unkind Blows fall on us, we may know for whoſe ſake it is,</hi> pag 3. He and his Legion are againſt neither Great, nor Small, but <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s King. Its againſt the <hi>Light,</hi> the Power of God his Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle is pitcht, ſayes this <hi>Water-Baptiſt, Its their Light Within, whom I withſtand.</hi> Alas! neither <hi>he,</hi> nor all the <hi>dark powers</hi> on Earth ſhall be able to extinguiſh it, whoſe Growth and Increaſe in deſpight of all their Oppoſition over-ſpreads the people not only in this Nation, but alſo in the Iſlands afar off; This ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts <hi>be</hi> his Enemy, and why? for any other cauſe, but by reaſon it tells him the Truth when he heeds it? This would he charge with all the <hi>Villanies</hi> and <hi>Enormities, that ever were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted,</hi> ſayes this <hi>Water-Baptiſt, to ſhew to what Enormities the pretended Light leads them.</hi> Let me tell thee, Has there been one that has cauſed thee to ſpeak Evil of the Wayes of God, he ſhall bear his Iniquity: but know, thou ſhalt not eſcape the Judgments of the Lord, who hateſt the Light, and comeſt not thereto for Reproof.</p>
                  <p>But certainly, thou comeſt up to, if not exceedſt the vileſt of Men, to charge <hi>groſs Miſcarriages</hi> upon that, which many of thy own Party acknowledge <hi>God's Gift, and good in its place;</hi> they will at leaſt ſay. <hi>Its the Light of a Natural Conſcience;</hi> or <hi>of the Moſaical Law,</hi> or <hi>the Reliques of that Impreſſion, that was in our firſt Parents, which ſhews Moral Duties, and to know there's a God, &amp;c. But,</hi> ſayes this <hi>Water Baptiſt, it leads them to Enormities:</hi> which yet he neither has, nor can prove. I muſt acknowledg, that if he takes this for good Arg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ment. If a Perſon having been Water-dipt, and owned the <hi>Water-Baptiſt-</hi> Faith, and whilſt amongſt them commits one or other Enormous Crime, or Wickedneſs, for which they diſown him, or caſt him out of their Fellowſhip, or Communion; if the Cauſe of his Miscar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages muſt be charged upon their Faith-Ordinances, and not his Diſobedience to what he profeſt; then <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> deals with us, as he would be dealt withal; elſe not. Again, the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſconalian, Preſbyter, Independent, Water Baptiſt, &amp;c.</hi> all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the holy <hi>Scriptures</hi> to be their Rule for <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:99793:27"/>daily Miſcarriages being acted, and fallen into by Perſons un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thoſe Names, or Diſtinctions, ſhall it be ſaid, See what <hi>Enormities</hi> the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> lead them into? No; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs: no more is the Light of the Son of God to be charged by Reaſon of him who profeſſed his Truth, but held it in unrighteouſneſs: but as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>If we walk in the Light, as he is in the Light, then have we Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip one with another, and the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſeth us from all Sin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So the Light is clear from <hi>R. Hobb</hi>'s his dark Impoſitions and our Fellowſhip clear from him, and all ſuch unfruitfull Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Darkneſs. But to cloſe his Charge, he exhorts againſt the <hi>Light within</hi> (Terming it <hi>the dark Imaginations of our own Heads</hi>) and rather to follow the Council of the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> which he <hi>Sophiſtically</hi> words thus: <hi>we have a more ſure word of the Prophets</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>meaning the Scriptures, to which we do well if we take heed</hi> (mark) <hi>as to a Light that ſhineth in a dark place,</hi> &amp;c. when as our Tranſlation is, <hi>word of Prophecy,</hi> and not <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> as the <hi>Water-Baptiſt</hi> inſinuates, and whence he comments, that the <hi>word of Prophecy</hi> there ſpoken of is the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and not the Teſtimony of Jeſus, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.10.</note> the Spirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy; although the <hi>Latin</hi> and <hi>Greek,</hi> as well as <hi>Engliſh</hi> has it <hi>word of Prophecy, Lat. verbum Propheticum,</hi> and the <hi>Greek</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>And if at this rate he can for his wicked End thus make bold with the holy <hi>Scriptures;</hi> I Queſtion not, but he will wreſt and expound his <hi>Oppoſers</hi> words to the like Purpoſe, yet I doubt not but to his own ſhame and <hi>Confuſion,</hi> which I ſhall deſcend to <hi>examine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. That I may not wrong <hi>R. Hobbs,</hi> who truly ſpeaks the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of his matter at the firſt, take his own words at large. (ſaith he) <hi>This Quakers Looking Glaſs is falſe, it preſents two Faces; one as if they did, another as if they did not own</hi> Charles Bayly <hi>for an eminent Quaker.</hi> And that this is ſo, ſee what he ſaith Pag. 10, viz. <hi>ſome new converted Friends,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>did own Charles Bayly;</hi> But the Men-Friends, ſaith he, (meaning himſelf and three or four more Priſoners in the Caſtle) did not own him ſo much.</p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:99793:28"/>
                  <p>Here's the <hi>Water-Baptiſts Charge</hi> naturally dividing it ſelf into theſe particulars, which I ſhall briefly examine and anſwer.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> affirms that <hi>L. Howard</hi> in Pag. 10, of his Book ſhould ſay, <hi>that ſome new converted Friends did own</hi> Charles Bayly, viz. <hi>for an eminent Quaker.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. But the Men-Friends (meaning himſelf and three or four more Priſoners in the Caſtle) <hi>did not own him ſo much.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. Then to the firſt <hi>Charge,</hi> that <hi>L. Howard</hi> ſaith, <hi>that ſome new converted Friends did own</hi> C.B. <hi>for an eminent Quaker,</hi> I Anſwer that in Pag. 10. or any other page of his whole Book there is not any ſuch matter, or any ſuch Expreſſion of <hi>L. Howard;</hi> nay, ſo much from it, and <hi>L.H</hi>'s words ſo far di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, to what this <hi>Impoſtor</hi> would impoſe, that they are clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly otherwiſe, for <hi>Luke</hi> reciting <hi>R Hobbs</hi> his Expreſſion in his <hi>Letter</hi> of <hi>June</hi> 10 1672. Where <hi>Hobbs</hi> alledges, <note place="margin">Pag. 17. of their Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative.</note> 
                     <hi>that if the Quakers ſhould deny</hi> Charles Bayly <hi>to be owned as a very eminent Man amongſt them (at the Time of his impriſoment) that then they will render them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the falſeſt Perſons, that over profeſſed Religion.</hi> Which Averment of the <hi>Water-Baptiſt L. Howard</hi> fully anſwers, and at the Cloſe of his <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> to that Point he tells them, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them at Liberty</hi> (which then few were) <hi>there were ſome, which did not own</hi> C.B. <hi>ſo much, as</hi> R. Hobbs <hi>reporteth of:</hi> which <hi>Luke</hi> deſcends to <hi>particulars</hi> to ſhew. Which way of Anſwer to the <hi>Water-Baptiſts Charge</hi> is both proper and full, giving not the admittance to his Conſtructions, much leſs to affirm, that <hi>Luke Loward</hi> ſaith, <hi>Some own'd him to be a very eminent Man amongſt them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>Water Baptiſt</hi> charges <hi>L. H.</hi> for ſaying, <hi>the Men Friends</hi> (meaning himſelf, and three or four more Priſoners in the Caſtle) <hi>did not own him ſo much.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Here <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> turns <hi>Critick</hi> advancing his bald <hi>Criticiſms</hi> to ſuch a bulk, that they bear the Burthen of his enſuing <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe:</hi> Not ſo much four or five times repeated in two Pages, yet an abſolute Forgery. Had the Man ſpoke this only to his <hi>Watery Auditory;</hi> it might upon his <hi>ipſe dixit</hi> have paſſed for <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox;</hi> but he muſt give us leave to tell him, that he by his <hi>Lines
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:99793:28"/>in Print</hi> has horridly wronged his <hi>Oppoſer,</hi> and as conſiderably abuſed his <hi>Reader:</hi> for <hi>L. Howard</hi> has neither word or Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that imports any ſuch matter, as he moſt audaciouſly charges: nay, ſo far were the Men from little or more joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with <hi>C. Bayly</hi> in Prayer, which is the <hi>Water-Baptiſt's charge</hi> of owning of him, that they had not Liberty of <hi>Acceſs</hi> to him, being then Priſoners in <hi>Dover-Caſtle,</hi> yet inſinuates the <hi>Water-Baptiſt</hi> from this (and that as the words of <hi>L. Howard</hi>) <hi>The Men owned him, but not ſo much.</hi> Certainly, the Man was hard put to it, that thus ſtraind to eaſe himſelf; could not ſelf-Evidence of this <hi>Antiquated Relation</hi> againſt an <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> ſeparated from us ſo many Years ago, have been a <hi>Probatum</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to have decided the Controverſie betwixt us, but it muſt be thus redoubled, not only once, nor twice, but with more renewed Inſtances of Lying Abuſe, and Impoſture to the Shame of himſelf, and Sorrow of the Flock to whom he affirms to be a <hi>Paſtor.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. And out of theſe very words <hi>ſo much</hi> has this mighty <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> framed the very Pillets of his Building: ſo by <hi>Theft</hi> and <hi>Violence</hi> makes be a <hi>Fortreſs</hi> againſt us. Remember <hi>R. Hobbs, though ſtoln Waters be ſweet; her Gueſts be in the Depths of Hell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Certainly, had <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> taken a doſe of Opium, he could not have more <hi>intoxicated</hi> his Brains then he has by this <hi>Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of <hi>Conteſt.</hi> And to ſee an inſtance hereof, take his own Words</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In pag. 1. of his <hi>Reply</hi> ſpeaking of his <hi>Antagoniſt; we know not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but that he owned Bayly as much as the Reſt did;</hi> well them, where's the Owning? Said <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> pag. 1. <hi>It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by their then affirming and juſtifying him to be led by the True Light, as they did by their hearing him preach, and devoutly joyning with him in prayer,</hi> Is this proof ſufficient? Said <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing the <hi>Queſtion, If this be not a ſufficient proof they own'd him. I know not what is, or can be ſufficient; nor do I know any Rule the Quakers have, by which I ſhall know when they own one another.</hi> Here our <hi>water-Baptiſt</hi> tells us, <hi>if this be not the Quakers Rule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o own one another</hi> he's at's wits end; for <hi>he knows no other.</hi> But what, will not he turn back, and ſhew us his other ſide? yes:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:99793:29"/>after <hi>R. Hobbs</hi> has told his <hi>Reader</hi> this fair Tale, that <hi>L. Howard own'd</hi> C. Bayly <hi>as much as any,</hi> and the only proof of owning him was, by joyning in Prayer, &amp;c. and <hi>if that was not ſufficient Proof; he knew not what was:</hi> he bringing again an <hi>Objection</hi> of <hi>L. Howard, that he and ſome more were in Priſon, did not own him ſo much</hi> (obſerve <hi>L. Howard</hi> uſes not that Expreſſion of <hi>ſo much,</hi> but its <hi>Hobbs</hi> his Forgery) which Negation of <hi>L. Howard</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> thus anſwers: <hi>If by</hi> ſo much <hi>you mean, you did not joyn with him in his Devotion, I grant it; for your Reſtraint from him hindered you in that.</hi> What's now become of the <hi>only owning?</hi> all this <hi>(ſo much)</hi> faln in the Dirt by a down-right contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. How well then our <hi>Water-Baptiſt</hi> has proved his <hi>Charge</hi> upon his <hi>Antagoniſt,</hi> I leave it to the <hi>Conſiderate Reader.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But more of Confuſion I have not often found in ſo brief a Writer; And I cannot but take notice of this Impoſtors Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, that in deſpight of all his forgeries and lying Citati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>L. Howard's Anſwer</hi> to his firſt confuſed <hi>Relation,</hi> yet he's ſo audacious to affirm; <hi>that he ſays no more of</hi> Luke, <hi>then he himſelf confeſſeth:</hi> when <hi>Luke Howard's</hi> words, ſentences and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions are as oppoſite to the <hi>Water-Baptiſt's</hi> proteſts and aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of them, as Light to Darkneſs it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R. Hobbs,</hi> let me adviſe thee as a Friend, to receive <hi>Luke Howard's Book;</hi> and thy own Reply, and paſs Juſt Judgment upon thy own Work: if not, give me thy Reaſon Let not thy Zeal, and rage againſt us ſo blind thy underſtanding to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſuch monſtrous effects; and after thou haſt inſpected thy own untimely Birth, and ſeen as well as thy <hi>Reader,</hi> of how little weight thy way of Argument is to rectifie the miſtakes, or reſolve the Doubts of the unprejudiced and unbyaſſed Inquirer at this day. Anſwer me, whether if thy old piece of envy and new-vampt <hi>ſtory</hi> of <hi>C Baily</hi> were really true as to him-wards, what do's it more concern us, then the many hundreds, that about the year 1660. and ſince <hi>Apoſtatized</hi> from you; yea, many of your <hi>Paſtors</hi> and Teachers, that have <hi>Revolted,</hi> and ſome to that <hi>Perſwaſion</hi> you frequently ſtigmatize us with all, as being moſt <hi>obnoxious</hi> to the Guſt of the people? We have generally for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born to put them, and their Miſcarriages in Print, as being weak Arguments to found <hi>Religion,</hi> knowing that as well in the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:99793:29"/>
                     <hi>primitive</hi> times, and the firſt Apoſtolick dayes, as in theſe Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ages there were ſtill ſuch, who made Shipwrack of Faith and a good <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and cauſed the Name of God and his Truth to be blaſphemed and evil ſpoken of; and ſo it is now.</p>
                  <p>But why doſt thou quarrel, <hi>that an Account of our Friends dealing with</hi> C. B. <hi>was not daily brought to thee?</hi> Its more, then the <hi>Roman Prieſt's</hi> themſelves <hi>deſire</hi> of perſons not nearer related, then thou and us. Muſt thou be a <hi>Confeſſor;</hi> elſe no plain deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? muſt we acknowledge to thee all paſſages of Chriſtian Care to one or other, elſe juſtifie an Evil-doer? ſtrange Infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence! Its ſcarce that time of Day: when thou haſt power, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it; till then, thou and thy <hi>Calumny reſt together.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I cannot but obſerve, how natural it is for this <hi>water-Baptiſt</hi> to correct his <hi>Antagoniſt;</hi> yet himſelf double guilty of being more like a Scold, then a ſober Chriſtian: truly next after a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal knowledge of both, I recommend their Books to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate <hi>Reader;</hi> who may with eaſe determine, where the fault lies: beſides <hi>Luke Howard</hi>'s ſolid behaviour in <hi>Dover</hi> has not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoke him the ſcurrilous term of <hi>wanton and lewd Ranter</hi> as this <hi>wicked water-Baptiſt</hi> moſt falſly inſinuates; whoſe upright Life, and ſober <hi>Converſation</hi> never merited ſuch unjuſt dealing from this Traducer, or any other. And ſo, I <hi>Juſtly Charge</hi> it upon him, as a falſe <hi>Accuſation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And to evidence, <hi>what ſpirit he is of,</hi> the very <hi>dialect</hi> he writes in, and his own Work will eaſily <hi>Diſcover:</hi> Have we more <hi>Modeſt Expreſſion</hi> from him, then the <hi>vileſt</hi> or <hi>debaucheſt</hi> of men, canting at us, as if meer <hi>Laſcivious</hi> and wanton. It he <hi>menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> the Women of our Friends, guibing at them thus, <hi>Their Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Companions.</hi> and ſuch like airy <hi>Epithetes:</hi> if Sufferers; <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the quaking account,</hi> and <hi>quaking Principles,</hi> with many more out of that Treaſury of Envy and Hatred, which in ſtore he has long horded up againſt us, and now belches it out, as an unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury ſtink in the Nation.</p>
                  <p>I have read over the whole <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> of two Sheets; and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I think, the Preſs is not very often troubled to ſo little, or ſo ill <hi>purpoſe:</hi> and did not the <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> of the <hi>Printer</hi> exceed the <hi>Ingenuity</hi> of the Writer, I Judge he had never paſſed h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> pittiful <hi>Pamphlet.</hi> As to what is more in his piece, its either ſuch, as
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:99793:30"/>falls under the <hi>apparent nullity</hi> of the Forgers <hi>Arguments;</hi> or with the <hi>confuſed</hi> heaps of his meer <hi>Impoſturs,</hi> and <hi>Abuſe.</hi> And if any thing elſe <hi>remains deſerving Regard,</hi> 'tis in the Knowledge of ſuch, whoſe <hi>perſonal acquaintance</hi> with the <hi>Forger</hi> and <hi>Fact</hi> can more <hi>properly</hi> anſwer, if not ſtop the Mouth of this <hi>envious,</hi> and <hi>confuſed Babler,</hi> with whom I leave him, and his <hi>Piece,</hi> as they ſee <hi>cauſe</hi> for further <hi>Reproof</hi> and <hi>Examination.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>London,</hi> 
                        <date>the 1ſt Mon. 1673.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Thomas Rudyard.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="postscript">
                  <head>A Poſtſcript.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe Word of the Lord came unto the true Prophet</hi> Ezekiel <hi>againſt the falſe and fooliſh</hi> Prophets, <hi>who followed their own</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, <hi>and therein propheſied Lyes, and falſe Divinations, and cauſed people to Err: And he ſaid,</hi> Wo unto the Fooliſh Prophets, who follow their own ſpirit, and have ſeen nothing. <hi>And God ſaid,</hi> Mine Hand ſhall be upon the Prophets that ſee Vanity, and that divine Lyes, they ſhall not be in the Aſſembly of my People, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3, 6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>And hath raiſed True Prophets in this Age to cry againſt the Falſe Prophets, and particularly againſt</hi> Charles Bayly, <hi>who was many Years ago judged and denyed by the Prophets and Servants of the Lord, becauſe he propheſied Lyes and falſe Divinations by the Leadings of his own unclean ſpirit, which ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in his deceitful Heart: and becauſe of theſe things he hath been ſhut out of the Aſſemblies of God's People</hi> (<hi>in Scorn called</hi> Quakers) <hi>for many years, although he ſometimes appeared amongſt them, as the falſe Apoſtles and deceitful Workers did in the dayes of the true Prophets and Apoſtles appear amongſt them; and as the true then judged, and denyed the falſe; ſo have we done unto</hi> C. B. <hi>in and with the Light, Life and Spirit of God, and of his beloved Son Jeſus Chriſt; and in and with the ſame we do and ſhall judge all</hi> Dreamers <hi>and</hi> Propheſiers <hi>of</hi> Lyes <hi>and</hi> falſe Divinations, <hi>who follow their own corrupt, ſinful
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:99793:30"/>and unclean ſpirits, from which the Myſteries and Secrets of the holy pure God lie hid. And now</hi> Richard Hobbs, <hi>who ſayſt,</hi> That <hi>C. B.</hi> was led by the <hi>Quakers</hi> Spirit in that Deluſion which he was given up to: <hi>If by the</hi> Quakers Spirit, <hi>thou doſt mean the</hi> Quakers Light, <hi>which thou ſo much ſcoffeſt at, which I have cauſe to believe by thy own words in thy Book thou doſt mean; then I do tell thee, thou doſt ſpeak</hi> Blaſphemy againſt God, <hi>who is</hi> Light; <hi>and againſt his beloved</hi> Son, <hi>who is the</hi> expreſs Image of his Subſtance, &amp; Brightneſs of his Glory. <hi>For I do tell thee, and all others, unto whom theſe Lines may come, That we the People of God called</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers <hi>have never preached up, or directed any man or woman unto any other Spirit or Light, wherein and whereby Salvation is brought unto the Immortal Souls of Men and Women; but the</hi> Spiritual Light <hi>of</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Chriſt, who is that Light, who lights every man that comes into the World, <hi>John</hi> 1.9. and 8.12. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.5, 6, 7. God, who commanded Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs, hath ſhined in our Hearts, to give us the Light of the Knowledge of the Glory of God in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt; and his Treaſure have we in Earthen Veſſels, that the Excellency of the Power may be of God, and not of us, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6, 7.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>W. G.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
